<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Confidence corrected, error detected, and truth defended; or Some farther reflections upon the two Athenian Mercuries lately publish'd about infant-baptism. By Philalethes Pasiphilus.</title>
            <author>Pasiphilus, Philalethes.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80339</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5803A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223470</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47682877</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47682877</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172831</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80339)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172831)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2652:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Confidence corrected, error detected, and truth defended; or Some farther reflections upon the two Athenian Mercuries lately publish'd about infant-baptism. By Philalethes Pasiphilus.</title>
                  <author>Pasiphilus, Philalethes.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the Year, 1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p.51.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Athenian mercury.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172831:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CONFIDENCE Corrected, ERROR Detected, AND TRUTH Defended; OR Some farther REFLECTIONS Upon the TWO <hi>Athenian Mercuries,</hi> Lately Publiſh'd about INFANT-BAPTISM.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Philalethes Paſiphilus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mar. 16.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that believeth and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Act. 8.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When they believed <hi>[Philip]</hi> preaching the things concerning the Kingdom of God, and the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, they were baptized, both Men and Women.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Act. 18.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>—Many of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> hearing, believed, and were baptized.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Col. 2.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Beware leſt any Man ſpoil you through vain Deceit, after the Traditions of Men, and not after Chriſt.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mar. 7.7, 8,</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>In vain do they worſhip me, teaching for Doctrines, the Commandments of Men. For laying aſide the Commandment of God, ye hold the Tradition of Men, as the waſhing of Pots, and Cups: <hi>(and as we are now told, Men, Women and Children too)</hi> and many ſuch like things ye do.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172831:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172831:2"/>
            <head>Confidence Corrected, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is a ſad Thing, and much to be <hi>lamented,</hi> that there ſhould continue to this Day, not only ſo many Differences in point of <hi>Judgment</hi> amongſt Chriſtians, but alſo ſo much <hi>Pride,</hi> and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice</hi> of Spirit one againſt another, by Reaſon of the ſame; inſomuch, that there can hardly be the leaſt Difference imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable amongſt Profeſſors of Chriſtianity in Matters of Judgment, but they are too readily turn'd into ſo many Marks of <hi>Reproach,</hi> and Cauſes of <hi>Malignity,</hi> one againſt another. This has been very ſadly experimented in this Nation, for many Years paſt; and, to this Day, finds but too much Entertainment in the Minds of many, who ſtill reckon themſelves Men in <hi>Reputation,</hi> for <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Honour.</hi> But, though it may juſtly be expected, do what we can, that there will ſtill remain <hi>Differences</hi> in Judgment, and <hi>Controverſies</hi> among Chriſtians in ſome things; yet of all the <hi>Controverſies</hi> that ever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd upon the Stage of Chriſtianity, I cannot but moſt of all <hi>admire</hi> at this <hi>Controverſy</hi> about <hi>Infant-Baptiſm:</hi> And that chiefly upon two Accounts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That ever it ſhould become ſuch a Controverſy as it has done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> At the ſtrange Effects that it has produced.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I cannot but admire, how this ever became ſuch a Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy amongſt Chriſtians, as it hath done; eſpecially amongſt ſuch Chriſtians, as do daily <hi>profeſs</hi> and <hi>declare,</hi> that the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are the only Rule of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> the only Guide to all Duty and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, relating to everlaſting Happineſs; whenas there is not the leaſt Word, nor ſhadow of a Word (and that by the Confeſſion of Parties) for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> in all the whole Book of God. I cannot imagine what the <hi>matter</hi> ſhould be, that Men ſhould make a <hi>Trade,</hi> of ſtraining their <hi>Wits,</hi> to find out ſo many <hi>Tricks</hi> and <hi>Inventions,</hi> to maintain and defend a Practice, and count it part of <hi>God's Service</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> that they know, and are convic'd in their Conſciences (as appears by their frequent Acknowledgments) is no where to be found in God's Word. There is ſcarcely any other Controverſy, that ever
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172831:3"/>happen'd in the World among Chriſtians, but makes a greater pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to <hi>Scripture</hi> than this doth, or can: It is not ſo much to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, that there has happened ſuch a Difference among Chriſtians about the Tenets of <hi>Arminius</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> about <hi>Abſolute</hi> and <hi>Reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Election</hi> and <hi>Reprobation,</hi> and all the <hi>Appurtenances</hi> belonging thereunto; becauſe there pretty plainly ſeems to be ſome conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Glances</hi> in Scripture in favour of both Opinions: yea, the very <hi>Socinians</hi> themſelves, (which deny the Deity of Chriſt) challenge a far fairer Pretence to Scripture, than any <hi>Pedo-baptiſt</hi> can do; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Text plainly ſaith, <hi>My Father is greater than I:</hi> Which as little as it is, if the <hi>Pedo-baptiſts</hi> could but produce ſuch a Glance as that, in Scripture, for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> it would be more than ever yet was done upon that account. Yea, the very <hi>Papiſts</hi> are leſs to be wondred at, in their Plea for <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> becauſe the Text ſaith plainly, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> &amp;c. Which is a Plea, beyond what any <hi>Pedo-baptiſt</hi> can pretend unto, in the behalf of that which they make ſuch a ſtir about. Yet how is the Weakneſs and Folly of <hi>Socinians</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and others, condemn'd and cenſur'd by many <hi>Pedo-baptiſts,</hi> whilſt they <hi>magnify</hi> and <hi>bleſs</hi> themſelves in that for which they cannot produce even ſo much ſeeming Authority from Scripture.</p>
            <p>I queſtion not, but I may preſume, that if a hundred of the moſt Learned and Judicious Men in the World, ſhould read the Bible o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forty times from one end to the other, they would never ſo much as think of <hi>Infant-baptiſm,</hi> by virtue of that Reading, and their beſt Conſideration into the Bargain, if the Voice of <hi>Tradition</hi> and <hi>Cuſtom</hi> had not poſſeſt them with it beforehand: and if ſo, how juſtly may it be wonder'd at, that ſuch a thing ſhould ever become a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy amongſt Pretenders to Scripture? — The <hi>Baptiſts</hi> ſay, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-baptiſm</hi> is no where to be found in Scripture: The <hi>Pedo-baptiſts</hi> frequently confeſs the ſame thing. — The <hi>Baptiſts</hi> ſay, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is not to be found in Scripture, is no Part of Divine Worſhip: — All <hi>Proteſtant Pedo-baptiſts,</hi> do freely acknowledg this alſo. Now who can tell where the Controverſy lies? Is it not ſtrange that Men ſhould pretend to differ, yea, and to differ greatly too, in that very thing wherein they ſeem to be ſo plainly and fully agreed? Who can give any good Reaſon now, why this <hi>Concluſion</hi> ſhould not neceſſarily be agreed to by mutual Conſent, namely, that <hi>Infant-baptiſm</hi> is no part of <hi>Divine Worſhip?</hi> Which if it were, the whole Controverſy would be gone at once. — The <hi>Baptiſts</hi> do from time to time aſſert,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172831:3"/>that there is neither <hi>Precept for,</hi> nor <hi>Precedent of,</hi> nor <hi>Promiſe unto,</hi> Infant-baptiſm, in all the Word of God: And their moſt Learned and Judicious Adverſaries, do frequently grant and confeſs the ſame thing; and yet ſtrive to maintain and uphold the Controverſy in the World. This is one Part of my <hi>Wonder,</hi> with reſpect to this Matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I cannot but wonder at the ſtrange Effects it has produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and they are many; but I ſhall only touch upon one, namely, That though the Principle and Practice of the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> (ſo called) is in the point of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> ſo plainly and plentifully laid down in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and holds ſuch an undeniable Correſpondency and Agreement with Primitive Purity, yet that they ſhould be loaded with ſo much Contempt and Reproach, as they have been, and yet are, by many in this Nation, for no other thing than this honeſt and harmleſs, yea, Honourable and Heaven-born Practice. Who is it that is any whit wiſe and judicious, that knows not that Chriſt and the Primitive Chriſtians were baptiz'd, as they now plead and practiſe? Yet how have they for many years, in this <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Kingdom, been not only ſlighted, but rendred odious, and counted as the very Dreggs and Off-ſcouring of the World, even for this very thing? Yea, the worſt and vileſt of Men, have been counted worthy of more Honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect amongſt People than they; inſomuch, that <hi>Highway-men</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> have been almoſt Titles of equal Dignity. Is it not ſtrange that any that pretend to be the Diſciples of Chriſt, and the Followers of Jeſus, ſhould dare ſo boldly to throw downright and naked Reproach upon the Practice of their Saviour; and caſt all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Dirt and Scorn in the Faces of any, meerly for endeavouring to follow him in that which he has not only commanded, but ſet them an Example in his own Perſon? — Though bleſſed be God, through the <hi>gracious Influence,</hi> and <hi>benign Aſpects</hi> of our <hi>Chief Rulers,</hi> this Spirit at this day is ſomewhat corrected and abated; yet to this moment, there are but too many that ſtill ſtrive to foment and cheriſh it. This is the ſecond Part of my <hi>Wonder,</hi> with reſpect to this Controverſy, above any other, that ever happen'd among ſober Chriſtians. — Now how far our <hi>Athenian Gentlemen</hi> have contributed towards the Removal of this <hi>Wonder,</hi> I ſhall take upon me the Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs a little to remark: — Wherefore now I ſhall direct my Diſcourſe to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I will not ſay, that you have ſo much beſpatter'd us with Dirt and Reproach, as ſome others have done before you; yet
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172831:4"/>I cannot but obſerve that you, at leaſt, ſeem to have a good mind, (if I may uſe ſuch a Soloeciſm) to be nibbling at it; and that appears chiefly, if we conſider theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt, How liberally and tartly you beſtow that ſilly and idle <hi>Nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name</hi> of Reproach <hi>[Anabaptiſt]</hi> upon us, ſo often repeated in your Papers? Though you know 'tis a Name we diſown and deny, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially too to do it at the ſame time that the Queſtion is <hi>militating</hi> betwixt us: Which indeed, beſides the <hi>Malignity</hi> that ſeems to be in it, is an implicite <hi>begging</hi> of the whole Queſtion. For what do you elſe, when you aforehand briskly take it for granted, that we are a Parcel of <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> making no <hi>Queſtion</hi> of that, when you know you are a diſputing that very Queſtion, which ought to <hi>determine</hi> whether we are ſo or no? Pray, Sirs, why may not we as juſtly make a trade of calling you, and all of your Party or Perſwaſion, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-baptiſts</hi> or <hi>Cata-baptiſts?</hi> for you cannot but know, that according to <hi>our</hi> Principles, you do as much <hi>deny</hi> Baptiſm, and <hi>abuſe</hi> it too, as we can poſſibly, according to <hi>your</hi> Principles, be <hi>twice</hi> Baptiz'd; but we reckon it below any that pretend to Wiſdom and Ingenuity, to make ſuch beggarly things any part of their Refuge: Wherefore, Sirs, I think I may ſafely conclude, you have not dealt ſo <hi>candidly</hi> with us in this Particular, as you ought to have done.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> In that you very unworthily, if not proudly, <hi>inſinuate,</hi> that there are none, nor ever were any among the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> that are ſo knowing in the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of <hi>Nations, Linguiſms, Radixes,</hi> or <hi>Original</hi> Significations in <hi>Languages,</hi> as you are; and that may perhaps be the great Cauſe of Diſputes upon this Subject: When, Sirs, it is very well known, that there have been, and are to this Day, many amongſt them, of very great <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> and excellently well skill'd in all thoſe Matters you talk of. Wherefore, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> if you are <hi>Ignorant</hi> herein, you might have done better to have kept your Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to your ſelves: But if you are not <hi>Ignorant</hi> hereof, there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can excuſe you from an <hi>invidious</hi> and <hi>ſpiteful</hi> Inſinuation. And you farther politickly expoſe them to popular Prejudice, by giving them a <hi>Paraliptical</hi> Bite, and by an <hi>Apophaſis</hi> cunningly charge them with a <hi>Spirit of Contention;</hi> which may alſo be a great cauſe of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes upon this Subject: As if your Opinion and Practice about <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> was ſo manifeſtly clear and evident, that it's ſcarce poſſible for any Body to make the leaſt Doubt or Scruple about it, if they be not afore-hand troubled with a <hi>Spirit of Contention;</hi> or elſe ignorant of the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of <hi>Nations, &amp;c.</hi> But pray, Sirs, Why a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172831:4"/>
               <hi>Spirit of Contention</hi> in the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> any more than in <hi>your ſelves?</hi> What's the Matter, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> that <hi>they</hi> muſt needs preſently be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be Criminals in this Caſe for diſputing, any more than their <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> that diſpute againſt them? Really, Sirs, if there muſt needs be a <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Contention</hi> on one ſide, it may with a little Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion eaſily be perceived, that it lies rather at <hi>your Door</hi> than at <hi>theirs;</hi> if you do but ſeriouſly reflect upon the <hi>Darkneſs</hi> of your own Practice, and the <hi>Clearneſs</hi> of theirs with whom you contend, <hi>Adverſaries</hi> themſelves being Judges.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly.</hi> In that you ſo impertinently and boldly mention ſeveral Perſons, whom you call <hi>Ring-leaders</hi> amongſt <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> who are ſuppoſed to be guilty of ſeveral Crimes, and remarkable Enormities; for no other end that can rationally be thought of, but to expoſe your <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> to farther <hi>Contempt</hi> and <hi>Prejudice.</hi> Here, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I cannot but admire at your <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> (if I had ſaid <hi>Folly,</hi> I think it had been no great matter) that you ſhould be ſo <hi>inconſiderately</hi> hardy, to venture upon ſuch an Argument as this.</p>
            <p>When, in the Firſt Place, we have juſt cauſe to queſtion the Truth of thoſe Things, as to Matter of Fact, being, as may rationally be ſuppos'd, firſt promoted by Lying and Malicious <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who ſpeak as bad things of <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Luther,</hi> and the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> before them: And may juſtly be thought, to be taken from them, by ſome <hi>inveterate Proteſtants,</hi> which bore them as little good Will as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> did, or Mr. <hi>Roſs</hi> himſelf. Alas! What ſtrange Work have we ſeen, even in our own Nation, upon this account? How many good Men have been miſerably miſrepreſented before our Faces, when there have been Thouſands alive, at the ſame time, that were able to have detected the Scandal, but durſt not attempt it? How many Men in <hi>England,</hi> have even been <hi>Diaboliz'd</hi> in the Face of the Sun, that in ſome time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter have been little leſs than <hi>Canoniz'd</hi> for <hi>Saints?</hi> and had it not been for remarkable <hi>Revolutions,</hi> had never recovered out of the ſhape of <hi>Devils.</hi> And amongſt many other Things, Mr. <hi>Roſs</hi>'s Brother <hi>Edwards</hi> his <hi>Gangrena,</hi> is too freſh in Memory to be forgotten.</p>
            <p>Secondly; If all were unqueſtionably true, you cannot chuſe but know there is no Argument in it, it is not only the <hi>weakeſt,</hi> but the <hi>worſt</hi> of Arguments; it greatly reflects upon the Wiſdom of any that ſhall venture to uſe it. For tho <hi>Hind, Hannam, Cutting Dick,</hi> and the <hi>Golden Farmer</hi> were all <hi>Villains;</hi> yet who doubts but there are many <hi>Pedo-Baptiſts</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and other <hi>Countries</hi> too, that are <hi>honeſt</hi> Men? and not only ſo, but their <hi>Principles</hi> too may be good, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing in this Argument againſt them.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:172831:5"/>
            <p>Thirdly; If there were any thing of Argument in it, who need matter it? Pray, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> conſider, who do you think has moſt cauſe to fear it, if there were any thing in it, <hi>they,</hi> or <hi>your ſelves?</hi> If they were diſpos'd to draw the Saw againſt you here, you may eaſily foreſee what dreadful and bitter work might be made with you, by virtue of this Argument. Really, Sirs, it argues you are heavily put to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and in a deſperate Caſe, that you dare venture up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch <hi>dangerous</hi> and <hi>ſelf-killing</hi> Methods: But you had better ſuffer a Famine of Arguments for ſeven Years together, than to meddle with ſuch <hi>Noli me Tangere's</hi> as theſe; for you cannot but know, that we might in this Caſe, give you <hi>Argumentum ad Hominem,</hi> at leaſt forty for one: And if ſo, then how wiſely you have done in this Matter, you may upon farther Thoughts become your own Judges. But I care not to inſiſt any farther upon this, unleſs we be farther fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhly provok'd.</p>
            <p>I now come to conſider how you anſwer the <hi>Queſtions</hi> about <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> chiefly in your Firſt <hi>Mercury,</hi> and the <hi>Second</hi> occaſionally, as there may be any freſh matter worth regarding.</p>
            <p>The firſt Queſtion you undertake to anſwer, is, Whether (as is commonly taught) <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is the proper and natural <hi>Antitype</hi> of <hi>Circumciſion?</hi> &amp;c. Your <hi>poſitive Anſwer</hi> is, that in many Caſes it will bear the <hi>Affirmative;</hi> which you endeavour to prove, from ſome fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>And your firſt is, from the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> in proſely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Gentiles</hi> into their <hi>Religion:</hi> So far indeed (ſay you) <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion</hi> was not properly a Type, but rather the <hi>Continuance</hi> of a <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> that by St. <hi>John,</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> had added unto it, all that was neceſſary to make it a full, proper, and pertinent <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> Now, Sirs, what a ſtrange, looſe, unintelligible and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfactory Anſwer is this?</p>
            <p>For firſt; Your <hi>poſitive Anſwer</hi> is not ſo <hi>poſitive</hi> as it ought to have been; for you do not <hi>poſitively</hi> anſwer the Queſtion at all, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was, or it was not a <hi>Tyye</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> Now this I humbly conceive you ought to have done, namely, <hi>poſitively</hi> to have aſſerted, that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was a Type of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> if you had look'd upon it ſo to have been, notwithſtanding they might have differ'd in ſome Circumſtances, as indeed all <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>types</hi> do in ſomething or other, otherwiſe they could not have been two, but one and the ſame thing: for things that <hi>differ</hi> not at all, cannot be <hi>different</hi> things. And divers things may agree with other
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172831:5"/>things, under ſome general Conſiderations, of which they never were <hi>Types,</hi> as well as thoſe that were: <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> were both Sons of <hi>Abraham;</hi> therein there was an Agreement. <hi>2dly,</hi> They were both Subjects of <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> there they agreed again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was no Type of <hi>Iſaac.</hi> A <hi>Horſe</hi> is a Subſtance, ſo is a <hi>Man,</hi> there's an Agreement; a <hi>Horſe</hi> is a Living Creature, ſo is a Man, there's an Agreement again; a Horſe eats and drinks, ſo does a <hi>Man,</hi> there's another Agreement; yet neither of them was ever a <hi>Type</hi> of the other: So that your <hi>poſitive</hi> Anſwer, does as ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imply that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was not a <hi>Type</hi> of Baptiſm, as it does that it was.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, Is it not ſtrange that ſuch Pretenders to <hi>Ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> as you are, ſhould bring a Conſideration to prove <hi>Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> a <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which as ſoon as ever you have laid down, you plainly confeſs and acknowledg it proves no ſuch thing, but rather the contrary? For do not you plainly tell us, that you ſhall endeavour to prove the <hi>Affirmative,</hi> by theſe following Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</p>
            <p>And the firſt is, From the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> amongſt the <hi>Jews;</hi> and yet in the very next Words, you tell us as plainly, it proves no ſuch Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: for ſo far it was no <hi>Type,</hi> but the <hi>Continuance</hi> of a <hi>Cuſtom.</hi> Pray, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> why then did you urge this Conſideration for ſuch a Purpoſe, when you knew beforehand, it was not capable of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming that Service? Methinks, you ſhould never be in love with ſuch a Cauſe, as doth ſo ſtrangly captivate your Intellects; as not only appears in this, but in other things that follow: <hi>Circumciſion</hi> (ſay you) was rather the <hi>Continuance</hi> of a <hi>Cuſtom, &amp;c.</hi> Now, Sirs, here I muſt of neceſſity be <hi>puzzled</hi> to find out your Meaning? Your Words are ſo unintelligibly laid down, that it will be hard for me to know what you intend by them; and if I ſhould, without any more ado, take that to be your Meaning, that the Order and Grammar of your Words here do imply, I know not but I might wrong you in your Meaning, which I would not willingly do if I could help it: I muſt be forc'd therefore, to gueſs at 2 or 3 things, and hit upon it if I can: Some one or other of which, I think muſt be your Meaning, or elſe I am like to continue ignorant of it till fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Revelation. Certainly theſe words <hi>Continuance</hi> of a <hi>Cuſtom</hi> here, muſt refer either to <hi>Circumciſion</hi> it ſelf, or elſe to that other <hi>Cuſtom</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews</hi> you ſpeak of; if to <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> as one might juſtly be under a Temptation to think it may, when you ſo plainly tell
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172831:6"/>us both <hi>Negatively</hi> and <hi>Poſitively,</hi> what it was not, and what it was; not a <hi>Type,</hi> but a <hi>Continuance</hi> of a <hi>Cuſtom;</hi> who can think but you muſt mean <hi>Circumciſion</hi> all this while? For how <hi>Circumciſion</hi> could be the Continuance of another thing, I do not well underſtand: if you had ſaid a Cauſe or Occaſion of Continuance, there might have been ſome ſmall matter in it, though not very much; but to be the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance it ſelf of another thing, is not eaſy to be perceiv'd. Now then, if this Paſſage of yours be referr'd to <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> then you on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell us, that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was a Continuance of <hi>Circumciſion:</hi> Which is ſuch a groſs <hi>Identity,</hi> as is not much incident to ingenious Men: But if we refer it to the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> among the <hi>Jews,</hi> then in the firſt place I ask, how could <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> which was a <hi>Precept</hi> of God, be the <hi>Continuance</hi> of another thing, that was only a <hi>Cuſtom</hi> among Men? Was the <hi>Practice</hi> and <hi>Continuance</hi> of the one, the <hi>Practice</hi> and <hi>Continuance</hi> of the other? or how would you be underſtood?</p>
            <p>Secondly; If your word <hi>Cuſtom</hi> here, relates to the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> aforeſaid, then you ſeem to ſay, it was that <hi>Cuſtom</hi> that St. <hi>John,</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> made a full, proper, and pertinent <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> and then it's ſo far from appearing that <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion</hi> was a <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which was the thing to be proved, that after all, it falls to the lot of this Jewiſh <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> to be this Type: Which our Saviour it ſeems, was ſo much in love with, that he and his Apoſtles, make it a Type of their own Baptiſm: Which is not only a very ſtrange thing, but wonderfully remote from your Purpoſe.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I would do you all the Juſtice I can, there is another thing which I have thought on, which may be your Meaning, for ought I know, but whether it is or no, that I cannot determine; but if it be, it is very far fetch'd, and muſt needs have a very uncouth Reference. However, the Suppoſition is this, namely, that St. <hi>John,</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> added to the old <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> all that was neceſſary to make <hi>Circumciſion</hi> a <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> And if ſo, then it's a plain Caſe, that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was never ordain'd or intended by God, neither in its Original nor Progreſs, to be a <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> till <hi>Baptiſm</hi> was made a Goſpel-Ordinance by <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> which is a very ſtrange and Self-contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting Notion. For if <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was ever a <hi>Type</hi> a <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> it muſt be ſo before ever <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> as a <hi>Antitype,</hi> could have a Being; for upon the Coming of the <hi>Antitype,</hi> the <hi>Type</hi> ceaſes: As ſoon as ever the <hi>Antitype</hi> lives and is in force, the <hi>Type</hi> dies
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172831:6"/>and is out of date: how then could <hi>Circumciſion</hi> be made a <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> by <hi>Baptiſm</hi> it ſelf? when according to this Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it muſt continue all its Life-long without ſuch a Title, and when it was dead, it could never come at it. If <hi>Circumciſion</hi> were not the <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> before <hi>Baptiſm</hi> came, how then could <hi>Baptiſm</hi> be the <hi>Antitype</hi> thereof? It could not come as an <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type,</hi> becauſe it ſeems there was no <hi>Type</hi> before it came. — If you had told us, that a Man cannot properly be ſaid to be <hi>born,</hi> till he is properly ſaid to be <hi>dead;</hi> or that the Father cannot properly <hi>Be,</hi> till the Son lives and begets him, it had been juſt ſuch a piece of <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> as this is of <hi>Divinity.</hi> — But if it be ſaid, that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> did not expire upon the coming in of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> for they were both in force for ſome Years together: I anſwer, it's very true, but then it's a good Argument to prove, that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> were never <hi>Type</hi> and <hi>Antitype.</hi> And this Suppoſition our Gentlemen do as good as grant, for they tacitly tell us, it was no <hi>Type</hi> before <hi>Baptiſm</hi> came, and how it ſhould be a <hi>Type</hi> afterwards, I know not.</p>
            <p>You ſay further, Had <hi>John the Baptiſt, Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. undertook any new Way of proſelyting the Jews to the Goſpel, they had not only ſtruggled with the Oppoſitions of a new Doctrine, but alſo of a new Practice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Really, Sirs, your Words here ſeem to imply, that it was ſome <hi>old</hi> Trade to proſelyte Men to the Goſpel long before it <hi>began;</hi> for if it was not ſome <hi>old</hi> Practice before, then it muſt be a <hi>new</hi> Practice, when St. <hi>John</hi> and our <hi>Saviour</hi> began it. And if the very proſelyting of Men to the Goſpel, were a <hi>new</hi> Practice, and the Doctrine leading there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, a <hi>new</hi> Doctrine, what force can there be in this <hi>Objection</hi> of yours? However, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> this Suggeſtion of yours, ſeems to be very raw and inconſiderate; for the great and principal Struggle of the <hi>Jews</hi> with our <hi>Saviour,</hi> was about his <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Authority;</hi> his being the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and ſent by his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> to teach and inſtruct the World, by virtue of that <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> which none ever before him had: And accordingly, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever our <hi>Saviour</hi> taught amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> he very frequently, not only reprov'd their vicious and enormous Lives, but corrected and condemn'd their falſe and erronious Doctrines, their idle and vain <hi>Traditions,</hi> and fooliſh Superſtitions, wherein they taught for <hi>Doctrines</hi> the Commandments of <hi>Men.</hi> And herein lay the chief Quarrel of the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt our <hi>Saviour,</hi> who inſtead of own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172831:7"/>of him in that <hi>Divine Capacity</hi> he juſtly challeng'd, they counted him a <hi>Samaritan,</hi> a <hi>Devil,</hi> and a <hi>Mad-man,</hi> contradicting, oppoſing, and charging of him with <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> for making himſelf <hi>equal</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> and condemning them in their Ways, as one that had <hi>Authority</hi> from Heaven ſo to do. — It was no part of our <hi>Saviour's</hi> Buſineſs, to countenance or encourage any in their vain <hi>Inventions</hi> and ſuperſtitious <hi>Fooleries,</hi> which were never <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed</hi> nor <hi>approved</hi> by God; but to enlighten their Minds, and take them off from all ſuch <hi>Dotages,</hi> and ſettle them upon ſuch things as were purely of God, and ſuch things as he had in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from his <hi>Father</hi> to teach them. — And give me leave to tell you, that if your Notion in this caſe, were ſuppos'd to be true, it cannot rationally be thought, that our <hi>Saviour</hi> could have made any great Earnings upon the ſtubborn <hi>Jews,</hi> by virtue of that; for if he had only taken their old <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> and alter'd it, or added any thing to it of his own Pleaſure, and made it what it was not before, (as you ſay) and given it out in his own <hi>Name,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring Obedience to it by his own <hi>Authority,</hi> even of the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, which never ſubmitted to it before, and that too in order to their being proſelyted or initiated into a new, or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religion; he would in ſo doing, have declar'd and aſſerted his <hi>Authority</hi> to them and over them, altogether as much as if he had requir'd a down-right <hi>new</hi> Practice of them; and have croſs'd their Humours and Inclinations as much in the one as in the other. And as for thoſe that were inclinable to fall in with his <hi>Authority,</hi> and to own his <hi>Divinity,</hi> as he himſelf aſſerted it, it may readily be taken for granted, that they would give him leave to give out what precepts he pleas'd, without ſtruggling with him about it: Thoſe that receiv'd his <hi>new</hi> Doctrine, would never contend with him about <hi>new</hi> Practice; for indeed, all <hi>Practice</hi> is comprehended in <hi>Doctrine:</hi> ſo that the ground of your Notion is altogether groundleſs.</p>
            <p>That Expreſſion of yours alſo, I muſt a little remark, as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther piece of <hi>crabbed Intricacy,</hi> which I cannot make very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Senſe of. When you tell as, that therefore this <hi>Cuſtom</hi> was continued, (namely, to pleaſe the Jews) and had the Superaddition of the full force of <hi>Baptiſm, viz.</hi> a <hi>Conſignation,</hi> or a <hi>Seal</hi> of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant: — Do not theſe Words now ſeem ſtrongly to imply, that there was ſome other <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in force as a <hi>Seal</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> which the Jewiſh <hi>Baptiſm</hi> had not the force of, till our <hi>Saviour</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:172831:7"/>takes it, and gives it now the full force of <hi>Baptiſm, viz.</hi> makes that <hi>Cuſtom</hi> a <hi>Seal</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> as well as <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> Baptiſm being the very <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Standard,</hi> unto which that <hi>Jewiſh Cuſtom</hi> was brought? for how could that <hi>Cuſtom</hi> have the full force of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> added, or given to it, if there had been no <hi>Baptiſm</hi> then in force, unto which this Jewiſh <hi>Cuſtom</hi> is now ſaid to be advanced? — And if ſo, then People may take their choice, whether they will have this laſt made <hi>Jewiſh Baptiſm,</hi> or the firſt made <hi>Chriſtian Baptiſm;</hi> for it ſeems, though they are two diſtinct <hi>Baptiſms,</hi> yet they are both <hi>Seals</hi> of the <hi>Covenant.</hi> Really, Sirs, it is not uſual for Men, in the face of the Sun, to ſpeak Daggers at this rate; No more would you, I conceive, if your undeſerving Cauſe did not force you to it. — I ſee it is not for nothing that you ſo freely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, in your ſecond Mercury upon this Subject, that you deliver'd your Aſſertions a little <hi>darkly.</hi> Indeed, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I think you were greatly in the <hi>dark</hi> when you wrote them, and therefore no wonder you were deliver'd of ſuch a <hi>dark</hi> Iſſue: Which though you ſeem to be ſenſible of, yet you ſeem to have no Inclination to come into the <hi>Light,</hi> that you may ſee to make better work. But, Sirs, after all this, I might juſtly enquire, how you came by all this Confidence? <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I beſeech you, who told you, or where did you read ſuch a piece of <hi>Chriſtian Divinity,</hi> as you ſo boldly <hi>dictate</hi> to the World; namely, that <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt, Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> did ſo highly approve of this old Jewiſh <hi>Cuſtom</hi> you talk of, as to take it, and put a Divine Sanction upon it, and make that very <hi>Cuſtom</hi> a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation,</hi> or a <hi>Seal</hi> of the Covenant, and ſo it became a proper <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type</hi> of <hi>Circumciſion?</hi> Does the Scripture, which we all pretend to be our Rule in Matters of Divine Worſhip, tell you any ſuch Story, or teach you any ſuch Doctrine? Is there the leaſt Whiſper of any ſuch thing in all the New-Teſtament? if there be, pray be ſo kind as to tell us where; if not, what ſignify your Dictates? Nay, Sirs, I am very apt to think, that your great Friend <hi>Maimonides,</hi> nor yet any of the Jewiſh <hi>Rabbies,</hi> ever told you ſuch a <hi>linſy-woolſy</hi> Story as this; yet here ſeems to lie the greateſt ſhew of your Proof that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was the <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> Sirs, if you did not ſeem to be a little proud and obſtinate in this Matter, I could hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily pity your Diſtreſs: but why ſhould you ſtrive, thus to impoſe your vain Crochets, and Scriptureleſs Notions upon us; and ſeem to be angry with us, that we do not greedily ſwallow them?</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:172831:8"/>
            <p>As for the three Texts you bring, further to prove <hi>Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> a <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which you call <hi>undeniable</hi> Texts; I confeſs, it might be worth any ones while, to take theſe three Texts, and read them well over; for they are, as the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> call them, <hi>undeniable</hi> Texts: But withal, do but remember for what purpoſe theſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> quote them, and then forbear ſmiling if you can. The <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I confeſs, were very much in the right, when they call'd them <hi>undeniable</hi> Texts: But they were extreamly in the wrong, when they thought theſe Texts would prove <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion</hi> a <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> or do them any ſervice for <hi>Infant-Sprinkling.</hi> The firſt Text is, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>In whom alſo ye are circumciſed with the Circumciſion made without Hands, in putting off the Body of the Sins of the Fleſh, by the Circumciſion of Chriſt; buried with him in Baptiſm, wherein alſo you are riſen with him, through the Faith of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of God,</hi> &amp;c. Now in the reading of this Text, any one might be ready to think, that certainly, if any thing here ſpoken of, may be ſuppos'd to be the <hi>Antitype</hi> of <hi>Circumciſion</hi> with Hands, it muſt be the <hi>Circumciſion</hi> here mention'd, made without Hands, in putting off the Body of the Sins of the Fleſh; and this is very ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, not only ſuggeſted, but (one would think) alſo very ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and fairly proved, by the <hi>Gentleman</hi> in his <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> as alſo in his <hi>Rejoinder:</hi> And alſo in that other <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s Anſwer to your two <hi>Mercuries.</hi> And indeed it lies ſo fairly in the Text, ſo eaſy to be underſtood, and ſo rational in it ſelf, that one may juſtly admire how any underſtanding Man could miſs it. But, ſay our <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> in their ſecond <hi>Mercury,</hi> The Scope of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here was to take off the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> from the Rudiments of the World, (then I hope, by the way, it was not to ſettle them in any old <hi>Cuſtom</hi>) eſpecially <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> which troubled moſt of the Churches; ſo far indeed, I ſhall not diſpute: And therefore, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> very wiſely and rationally gives them to underſtand, that they had not the leaſt occaſion to dote upon theſe weak and beggarly Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for, ſaith he, ye are <hi>compleat in Chriſt;</hi> (without them) <hi>in whom alſo ye are circumcis'd</hi> (if that be it you would have) <hi>with the Circumciſion made without Hands, in putting off the Body of the Fleſh,</hi> which is far better than your old outward <hi>Circumciſion;</hi> and this is plainly ſignify'd and confirm'd to you, in your being <hi>buried with Chriſt in Baptiſm:</hi> So that you have no reaſon in the World, to hanker after theſe unprofitable things, but rather much reaſon to be content in your <hi>Goſpel</hi>-Station, and keep where you are: being not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172831:8"/>only in a better Condition, in being deliver'd from that <hi>Yoke</hi> of Bondage, but alſo ſtrongly oblig'd to perſevere in the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, by being liſted under the <hi>Captain</hi> of it, by your being <hi>buried with him in Baptiſm, wherein alſo you are riſen with him, through Faith,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But ſay you, they might object, We want the outward <hi>Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> to us and our Children. No Sirs, they might not now object at this rate, for this was the Objection that was ſuppoſed to go before, unto which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> had given a very fair, full and ſatisfactory An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, by telling them that they were <hi>Circumciſed</hi> with the <hi>Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made without Hands,</hi> as aforeſaid: So no room for that Objection now. But this Interpretation is rejected, and condemned, by our <hi>Athenian Gentlemen;</hi> and <hi>Circumciſion</hi> muſt, even by this Text, be the Type of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> when all's done: But for what Reaſon I cannot imagine, unleſs it be meerly becauſe they find theſe two Words in the Text, <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> and therefore conclude one muſt be a Type of the other. But, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> if you will but let our Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation paſs for Orthodox till you are able to give us a better, we ſhall in this Caſe deſire no more. Moreover, Sirs, If we ſhould grant you your own Expoſition here, and give it you for Truth, I do not yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what great matter you would gain by it; unleſs we give you alſo what you pleaſe to beg for into the Bargain: What if I ſhould grant you, for Argument-ſake, that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> ſupplies the place, or came in the room of <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and that Chriſtians are in effect <hi>Circumciſed</hi> becauſe <hi>Baptized</hi> (as you ſay:) All this might be, and yet this Text ſignify nothing for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> unleſs it were alſo plain in the Text that Infants are the Subjects of it; but there is not the leaſt glimmering of ſuch a thing in the Text, but rather plainly the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: There's nothing in the Text but what is rationally excluſive of <hi>Infants.</hi> It cannot be ſuppoſed that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> is to be underſtood of <hi>Infants,</hi> when he tells the believing <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> that in Chriſt they were <hi>Circumciſed</hi> with the <hi>Circumciſion made without Hands, in putting off the Sins of the Fleſh, and were buried with Chriſt in Baptiſm, wherein alſo they were riſen with him through Faith,</hi> &amp;c. What therefore, if I ſhould now grant you that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in this Text ſhould intimate, that in the place and room of <hi>Infant-Circumciſion,</hi> Chriſt has now appointed <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Baptiſm;</hi> that inſtead of <hi>Abraham's Fleſhly Seed</hi> that were wont to be <hi>Circumciſed,</hi> he will now have only <hi>Abraham's Spiritual Seed</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized? As in the caſe of the <hi>Paſſover</hi> and the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> moſt judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Chriſtians do ſuppoſe and believe that the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> came in the room of the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> and that tho <hi>Infants</hi> did partake of the one,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172831:9"/>yet they are excluded from the other. Where then would your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage be, if we ſhould grant you that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> might come in the room and ſtead of <hi>Circumciſion?</hi> you would ſtill be as far to ſeek for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> as ever you were. For you know, it is not <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> running parallel in ſome things, that will make them parallel in every thing; and by the ſame Rule you grant them to differ in the caſe of <hi>Women,</hi> why may they not alſo differ in the caſe of <hi>Infants?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your other two Texts, is 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. the one ſpeaks of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> being <hi>baptized</hi> unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the Cloud, and in the Sea; and the other of <hi>Noah</hi> and his Family being ſaved in the <hi>Ark, &amp;c.</hi> Now let all the World judge how theſe Texts prove <hi>Circumciſion</hi> to be a <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> What courſe ſhall we take to frame an Argument from theſe Texts for ſuch a purpoſe? <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> becauſe I perceive you are ſuch Friends to a Syllogiſtical way of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I'le try how well I can do your work for you, which you ſeem to have no Stomach to do for your ſelves.</p>
            <p>Firſt, thus, <hi>If the Cloud and Sea were a Type of Baptiſm, then Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was a Type of Baptiſm:</hi> But this Text implies, <hi>That the Cloud and Sea were a Type of Baptiſm:</hi> Ergo, <hi>Circumciſion was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, <hi>If</hi> Noah<hi>'s Ark were a Type of Baptiſm, then Circumciſion was ſo: But</hi> Noah<hi>'s Ark was a Type of Baptiſm:</hi> Ergo.</p>
            <p>But if you think this <hi>Hypothetical</hi> way of Syllogizing is not ſo good as the <hi>Catagorical</hi> way; I'le try how they will look when they are laid down <hi>Catagorically.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then thus it muſt be; <hi>The Cloud and the Sea were a Type of Baptiſm: But Circumciſion was the Cloud and the Sea:</hi> Ergo, <hi>Circumciſion was a Type of Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Noah<hi>'s Ark was a Type of Baptiſm: But Circumciſion was</hi> Noah<hi>'s Ark:</hi> Ergo, <hi>Circumciſion was a Type of Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If our <hi>Gentlemen</hi> ſhould not like theſe Arguments, I would adviſe them to ſtudy a better Cauſe, that they may know how to mend them: In the mean time, whoever is in love with ſuch Logick, let them go to theſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> to learn it.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I have not yet done with your <hi>Jewiſh Cuſtom,</hi> I am willing to paraphraſe a little farther upon it before I paſs it: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in the firſt place, I muſt needs tell you, that I ſee no reaſon but why we may yet queſtion the very Truth of it, even with reſpect to matter of Fact; for although 'tis true I lay no great ſtreſs upon the Buſineſs, for I do not much care whether it be true or falſe; yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172831:9"/>but reckon it is at leaſt lawful to queſtion whether your Story be true or no, eſpecially a Truth of ſuch an ancient ſtanding as you talk of, and not only ſo, but a Truth ſufficient to make the <hi>Bottom</hi> and <hi>Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of a <hi>Goſpel-Ordinance.</hi> You had need of good Evidence, Sirs, to palliate your Boldneſs; but if you had far better Evidence than you have, as to Matter of Fact, it will not excuſe you in impoſing it upon us as a <hi>Goſpel-Duty:</hi> How great is your Folly then if it ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be but a <hi>Fiction,</hi> which ſeems at leaſt to be likely, if we ſeriouſly conſider theſe two or three Things?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> Becauſe there is not the leaſt mention of ſuch a Thing in all the Old and New Teſtament; the Scripture knows nothing of ſuch a Story, which is a very probable Argument to prove it falſe: For if there had been ſuch a remarkable <hi>Cuſtom</hi> amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> ſo long ago as you intimate, Is it not ſtrange, that neither <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor any of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> Writers, nor our <hi>Saviour,</hi> nor any in the <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> ſhould ever give us the leaſt hint of ſuch a Thing? And yet you confidently dictate, that our <hi>Saviour</hi> took that <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> and turn'd it into a <hi>Goſpel-Sacrament,</hi> and yet never gave us the leaſt Signification that ever there was ſuch a <hi>Cuſtom</hi> in the World: Which does, at leaſt, very ſtrongly imply one of theſe two Things. Firſt, That either there never was ſuch a <hi>Cuſtom</hi> in the World in thoſe Days; or if there was, our <hi>Saviour</hi> had nothing to do with it, at leaſt in your Senſe; your choice of either <hi>(Gentlemen)</hi> wholly deſtroys your Cauſe.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly;</hi> Matter of Fact may yet be doubted, becauſe, as far as I can yet perceive, this Story is originally taken out of the <hi>Jews</hi> Fictitious and Lying <hi>Talmud;</hi> in which is contain'd ſuch a Bundle of fabulous and ridiculous Stories, which almoſt every Man in his Wits is ſo far from believing, that they muſt rather conclude them to be abominable Falſhoods.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly;</hi> Becauſe, as Sir <hi>Norton Knatchbull</hi> obſerves, (as I find him quoted by Mr. <hi>Danvers</hi>) there is a difference in this Matter even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Jewiſh <hi>Rabbies</hi> themſelves: two eminent <hi>Rabbies</hi> that were Contemporaries, plainly contradicting each other in this Point, even as to matter of Fact; <hi>Eliezer</hi> affirm'd that the Proſelytes were <hi>Circumciſed</hi> and not <hi>Baptized,</hi> and <hi>Rabbi Joſhuah</hi> atteſted the quite contrary, that they were <hi>Baptized</hi> and not <hi>Circumciſed:</hi> Whereupon Sir <hi>Norton</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to which of them muſt we adhere, to <hi>Eliezer</hi> that affirms what the Scriptures teach, or to <hi>Joſhuah</hi> that aſſerts what the Scriptures no where teach? All theſe things well conſider'd, it ſeems to be more than probable to be but a lying Invention.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:172831:10"/>
            <p>I confeſs, had you not brought this Story as a <hi>Baſis</hi> of that which all Chriſtians count part of <hi>Divine Worſhip,</hi> I ſhould not ſo much have concern'd my ſelf in queſtioning the Truth of it, neither had your Weakneſs been ſo apparent, whether the Story had been true or falſe; we might have believ'd juſt what we had liſted in it without being one jot better or worſe. But now, Sirs, with reſpect to what you bring it for, nothing leſs than Scripture-Teſtimony ought to ſerve the turn; therefore your Diſingenuity (to ſay no worſe) appears to be exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great in going about to put us off with the Story of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, <hi>Cato</hi> and <hi>Hannibal.</hi> Alas! Sirs, we may make a pretty good ſhift to believe ſuch things as theſe, if Human Teſtimony do but hang well together about them, becauſe they are of the ſame Nature and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment with the Teſtimony that gives them; and if they ſhould happen to be falſe, yet our Souls have no Dependency upon them. But if any Body ſhall tell me that <hi>Alexander,</hi> or any Body elſe, conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> about Baptizing <hi>Bells</hi> and <hi>Pots,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtle's</hi> Anſwer was that it is a <hi>Chriſtian Duty</hi> ſo to do, 'tis part of <hi>God's Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip,</hi> and it ought to be done in the Name of the <hi>Sacred Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi> and ſhould refer me to ſome <hi>old Human Hiſtory</hi> to prove it by as a Divine Truth; I ſhall only ſay, that he that takes this for good pay, deſerves to be cheated.</p>
            <p>But Secondly; If your Story, as to matter of Fact, were unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionably true; and that it's ſo certain that the <hi>Jews</hi> had ſuch a <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> that none needs doubt it, this would be far from being ſatisfactory to the matter in hand: For firſt, Who bad them do it? Did they come honeſtly by this Cuſtom? Was it appointed and approved of by God, or was it not? If you ſay it was, you cannot but reckon your ſelves oblig'd to prove it: And if it was not of God, but their own Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Invention, what does it ſignify to us Chriſtians, any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than to admoniſh us to take heed that we do not provoke God by our fooliſh Inventions as they did? And can it be imagin'd that God ſhould aboliſh his <hi>own Appointments,</hi> and ratify and conſecrate one of their <hi>God-provoking Cuſtoms,</hi> as a Divine Sacrament in the room and place thereof, to be a binding Duty upon all Chriſtians? Sirs, if you dare aſſert ſuch a thing, you had need to have ſpecial Evidence to bear you out in it; and yet behold you have none at all, notwithſtanding you can venture very boldly to tell us that there was no need to have this expreſly ſet down, in what Method and what Perſons, whether <hi>Infants</hi> or not, the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> being ſo well known before-hand; when it may not only be queſtion'd, whether <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> knew
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172831:10"/>any thing of it, or whether you know any thing of it your ſelves from good Authority? But it's evident there are many thouſand in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World that know nothing at all of this <hi>Cuſtom;</hi> What muſt all theſe poor Creatures do that have nothing to inform them into their Duty in this matter, but the <hi>Scriptures?</hi> Do not you a little too plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give us to underſtand, that the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſignifies nothing to our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction or Direction herein? And if it be our Duty to baptize our <hi>Infants,</hi> we are like to know nothing of it from thence? But thoſe that are ignorant of the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> (as you intimate many are) muſt of neceſſity remain ignorant how to ſerve and pleaſe God in this particular, unleſs by conſulting the <hi>Jewiſh Talmud</hi> they can arrive at that Happineſs; for it ſeems by this Paſſage of yours it is in vain to conſult the Scriptures about it, <hi>Res ſtupenda &amp; horrenda!</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Second Queſtion you undertake to anſwer is this, <hi>What certain indubitable Grounds can we have for the practice of Infant-Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Anſwer is now direct and poſitive, <hi>from the Scripture.</hi> Gentlemen, I do aſſure you, I am very glad of this Anſwer; for then, I hope, we ſhall hear no more of that old <hi>Jewiſh Cuſtom,</hi> which has lain ſo long in our way: If you had thought of this ſooner, you might have ſav'd your ſelves and me too, a great deal of Labour: for hitherto, the <hi>Jewiſh Cuſtom</hi> has been the only Oracle that one would have thought, might have been ſufficient fully to have decided the Controverſy: for it does not only prove <hi>Circumciſion</hi> a <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> but it goes further, and anſwers the main <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> in that caſe; for though <hi>Women</hi> were not <hi>circumcis'd,</hi> and ſo one would think ſhould have been excluded from <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> No, not ſo; this <hi>old Cuſtom</hi> take, that quite off: for, inaſmuch as Men, <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> and Children, among the <hi>Heathen,</hi> were <hi>baptiz'd</hi> by the <hi>Jews,</hi> it wholly anſwers that Objection; and one would think, ſhould fully prove the whole Controverſy, that Men, <hi>Women</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> are all the Subjects of Baptiſm. Who could imagine, that after all this, we ſhould need to be beholden to the <hi>Scripture</hi> for <hi>Infant-baptiſm?</hi> But however, the caſe it ſeems is alter'd, the <hi>Scripture</hi> muſt now do the buſineſs: And I freely confeſs, that if it do but appear from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that either <hi>Infants</hi> were baptiz'd by God's Appointment, or ought to be Baptiz'd, we ought to be ſilent in the Caſe. But what Scriptures are theſe, that thus <hi>certainly</hi> and <hi>indubitably</hi> prove <hi>Infant-baptiſm?</hi> Why the firſt is, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 28. Good Reader, do ſo much as read the Text, and ſee elſe if it do not: Thus it reads, <hi>Go ye therefore, and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172831:11"/>and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt: Teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you.</hi> Certainly, Sirs, you muſt be <hi>Gentlemen</hi> by your Boldneſs, elſe you durſt not have ventur'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a Text as this, to have prov'd <hi>Infant-baptiſm:</hi> Sure you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but think, that any Text in the <hi>Bible</hi> will prove it as much as this; and there are abundance of Texts that have leſs in them <hi>againſt</hi> it. I wonder why you did not urge them by Dozens! But, Sirs, what reaſon had you to bring this Text for <hi>Infant-baptiſm?</hi> Does not the Text rather plainly exclude them, when it ſaith, <hi>Go, teach</hi> all Nations, and then <hi>baptize</hi> them? Pray, Sirs, conſider, and anſwer plainly, if you dare venture to be ingenuous; Is any <hi>more,</hi> or any <hi>other,</hi> here commanded to be <hi>baptiz'd,</hi> than what are firſt commanded to be <hi>taught,</hi> and that too, by the Apoſtles preaching of the Goſpel to them, as it is expreſs'd in <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15, 16. a parallel Place, where this ſame Commi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion is repeated? If this be not excluſive of <hi>Infants,</hi> I wiſh you would let us know what is. But, ſay you, the Order of Words in the Commiſſion, does your buſineſs: Well, Sirs, if it do, we are well contented; for we are very well pleas'd, with that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that our <hi>Saviour</hi> has here laid down: And I plainly perceive, that with all your Art and Learning, (though you ſeem to have a great mind to it) you are not able to <hi>diſorder</hi> them, to ſerve your purpoſe. The words in the Commiſſion, you ſay, is, <hi>Mathetéuſate pánta ta ethne,</hi> diſciple all Nations; and then follows, <hi>Baptizontes kai didáſcontes,</hi> and this you ſay, in your ſecond Paper, you ſhall ever ſtand by, (as the Senſe and Scope of this Commiſſion) to wit, <hi>diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> all Nations, <hi>Baptizing</hi> and <hi>Teaching</hi> them. Good now, Sirs, ſtand your ground; mean but honeſtly, and there's no danger of Diſcord from any that I know of. What do we ſay, or plead for, more or leſs, than you have thus far plainly given us? We freely grant, that the Word <hi>Mathetéuſate</hi> ſignifies to <hi>diſcipulize, diſciple,</hi> or make <hi>Diſciples:</hi> and this muſt be done, by this Commiſſion, before Perſons are to be <hi>baptiz'd:</hi> and when that's done, they are to be <hi>baptiz'd,</hi> and after that, <hi>ſtill</hi> to be taught, to <hi>grow in Grace</hi> and <hi>Knowledg,</hi> that they may <hi>go on to Perfection.</hi> Now, Sirs, if this be the thing you reſolve to ſtand by, we bid you <hi>God ſpeed;</hi> you will hardly meet with any Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters among the <hi>Baptiſts.</hi> Yet though you not only grant, but plead to this purpoſe, in your <hi>firſt</hi> Paper, and tell us you are reſolv'd to ſtand by it, in your <hi>ſecond:</hi> You have no mind we ſhould take this Senſe into <hi>our hands,</hi> though you know not well how to keep it in <hi>your own;</hi> neither have you any mind to keep to it <hi>your ſelves,</hi> when
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172831:11"/>all's done; for you ſtrangely ſtrive to ſhrink away from it, as ſoon as ever you have laid it down; and very odly make theſe two incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous Obſervations from the Text ſo read:</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Infants are not excluded from Baptiſm, as is generally believ'd by Anabaptiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>A Perſon may be baptiz'd before he be taught.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly, Sirs, you can never think, that theſe two Propoſitions receive Countenance and Confirmation from this Text: For firſt, If <hi>Infants</hi> are not excluded from <hi>Baptiſm</hi> by this Text, good now do ſo much as tell us who are. Secondly, If Perſons may be <hi>baptized,</hi> by this Text, without being firſt taught, pray be ſo kind as to tell us, who by this Text, are <hi>not</hi> to be <hi>baptiz'd.</hi> If you think none are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, or if there can be none in the World, that are <hi>not</hi> to be <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd,</hi> I wiſh you would tell us ſo in words at length, that we might readily give you the Reputation of <hi>extraordinary</hi> Doctors of Divinity. Pray, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> tell us alſo plainly, how you think the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> by virtue of this Commiſſion, were to make <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in order to their being <hi>baptiz'd:</hi> Were they to make People Diſciples of Chriſt, meerly by <hi>looking</hi> upon them, without <hi>ſpeaking</hi> a <hi>word</hi> to them? This indeed ſeems to be the Deſign of your ſtruggle in your two Papers; namely, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were to <hi>diſciple</hi> People to Chriſt, where-ever they came, without teaching them any thing in order thereunto. Which he that can believe, certainly need ſtick at nothing: for if People may be <hi>Diſciples</hi> of Chriſt, without being <hi>taught,</hi> then they may be Diſciples of Chriſt without <hi>learning</hi> any thing at all; and if ſo, then ſure one would think, that <hi>all the World</hi> ſhould <hi>in every,</hi> or <hi>any Capacity, ipſo facto,</hi> be Diſciples of Chriſt. And yet again, they were to be <hi>made</hi> Diſciples before they could be ſo; and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were to <hi>do</hi> ſomething in order to the <hi>making</hi> them ſo: but what that was, who can imagine, for they were not to <hi>ſpeak</hi> a <hi>word</hi> to them, to <hi>teach</hi> them any thing about it. Sirs, why do you ſtrive thus, by your confuſed Confidence, to deceive People, and bring them into a miſerable Maze? Beſides, if this were the Deſign of the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that the Apoſtles were to make Diſciples without Teaching, then theſe two things will follow: Firſt, That our <hi>Tranſlators</hi> of the Text, were either very <hi>Ignorant,</hi> and knew not how to tranſlate the Words as they ſhould have done; or elſe very <hi>unfaithful,</hi> that they did not: For they have, by their Tranſlation of the Text, given us occaſion to believe, almoſt whether we will or no, that <hi>Teaching</hi> muſt precede Baptiſm: and really, it ſeems to agree ſo mightily, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172831:12"/>with Reaſon it ſelf, but alſo with other Scriptures, that we can do no leſs than think it true. <hi>2dly,</hi> If this were the Senſe and Deſign of the Place, then if the Apoſtles had ever preſum'd to preach the Goſpel to any Body, <hi>before</hi> they had <hi>baptiz'd</hi> them, they had gone quite beſides their Commiſſion, and broke the Command of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: for either they were to teach People by this Commiſſion, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> they <hi>baptiz'd</hi> them, or they were not: if they were, then all your ſtrange Prattle to the contrary is gone; if they were not, then that which I have ſaid muſt follow: Or elſe there muſt be two Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions in this one, contra-diſtinct to each other, given out in the ſelf-ſame Words, which can be but of one Signification, and yet muſt be underſtood in two, quite contrary to each other; that is, you ſhall, and you ſhall not, teach People before you baptize them: And how conſonant theſe things are to Scripture and Reaſon, let all the World judg. But, alas! were it not for the ſake of the poor Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant World, that are apt to be taken with any thing you ſay, we need not take any pains to confute you; for after you had been <hi>ped<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> a while, to make Folks believe, that the Apoſtles were to make Diſciples <hi>without</hi> Teaching, you preſently, even in the Proſecution of your Proof, contradict and confute your ſelves: for you ſay, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetéuſate,</hi> which ſignifies, to <hi>diſciple all Nations,</hi> is a general Word, and contains in it the other two that follow: viz. <hi>Baptizontes kai di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dáſcontes,</hi> Baptizing and Teaching; <hi>the Commiſſion is to diſciple, and the Manner how, is Baptizing and Teaching;</hi> both it ſeems, as well as one; without which a Diſciple cannot be made. Is not this a clear Confeſſion, that <hi>Teaching</hi> is as neceſſary and eſſential to the making of Diſciples, as <hi>Baptizing?</hi> And if ſo, what will you do for <hi>Infant</hi>-Diſciples? Are you not as far to ſeek now, as ever your were? What are you the nearer, if this be true, to baptize your <hi>Infants,</hi> unleſs you <hi>teach</hi> them too? you even leave them as you found them, no more Diſciples of Chriſt, than they were before: and if ſo, had not you better ſtill let the <hi>Needle</hi> go before the <hi>Thrid,</hi> (or <hi>Teaching</hi> before <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing</hi>) than thus to ſtrive to teach the World a ridiculous Trade, and take a deal of Pains to no purpoſe? Though when all's done, it's very plain from Scripture, that Perſons may be made Diſciples of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Baptiſm, as indeed they ought, even by this Commiſſion of our Saviour; and that by <hi>Teaching</hi> too, and then to be <hi>baptiz'd:</hi> and this is not only agreeable to the Current of Scripture in many other places, but particularly moſt exactly to <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Jeſus made, and baptiz'd more Diſciples than</hi> John: firſt <hi>made</hi> them Diſciples, then they were <hi>baptiz'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:172831:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> You ſay, <hi>Children are capable of Proſelytiſm, as may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd from our Saviour's Words, Suffer little Children to come unto me; which your great Skill in the Greek, tells us is the ſame with, to proſelyte.</hi> Now how you would be underſtood here I know not, whether you reckon that their bare coming to Chriſt were their <hi>Proſelytiſm;</hi> or, whether they come to Chriſt with a deſign and purpoſe to be proſely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him ſome <hi>other way?</hi> If the former, then all that came to Chriſt (when he was upon Earth) upon any account whatſoever, (tho it was to betray him) were immediately by that very Act proſelyted to him, the Act it ſelf was their <hi>Proſelytiſm;</hi> but if they came with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and purpoſe to be proſelyted to Chriſt by any other way, as he pleaſed to direct and inſtruct them, then certainly they could not be ſuch <hi>eight-days-old Proſelytes</hi> as you frequently baptize. Now, Sirs, we deny not, but when Chriſt was perſonally upon Earth, little Children might either come to him, or be brought to him, upon divers occaſions, as well as others; and ſo far as that very thing made <hi>Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes</hi> of them, ſuch <hi>Proſelytes</hi> let them be, who ſhall hinder it? But then that Act muſt be perform'd, or elſe that <hi>Proſelytiſm</hi> has no being. But now Chriſt is not upon Earth; <hi>Ergo,</hi> there's no inſiſting upon this now: And whoever is capable of coming to Chriſt now, with a Deſign and Purpoſe to be <hi>proſelyted</hi> to him, by Faith, Repentance, Love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> let them be young or old, we are ſo far from hindring them, that we had rather do all we can to help them forward. But, if this don't pleaſe you, good now do ſo much as tell us plainly, what you mean by <hi>Proſelytiſm,</hi> when you ſay, <hi>Children are capable of Proſelytiſm;</hi> wherein lies their Capacity, or what is it they are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of doing? or whether there is any thing requir'd of them in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto? If any thing, what? If nothing, why are not all Proſelytes as well as any? or how ſhall we do to know the Capacity of a <hi>Believer's</hi> Child, from an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeliever's?</hi> If they are both <hi>alike</hi> in Capacity, then there is no <hi>difference:</hi> If there is a <hi>difference</hi> in the Capacity of the Children of <hi>Believers</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers,</hi> pray tell us where it lies; eſpecially, ſince the Children that came to Chriſt, were Children indefinitly: or whether it be any Child's <hi>Vertue</hi> to be a Proſelyte, or <hi>fault</hi> that it is not? or whether this young Proſelyte, you talk of, underſtands any thing more of the Mind of God in <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> with it, than it or another did, or may without it? For if it be no fitter for Baptiſm with it, than it or another is without it, pray what is it you talk of? For we ſay none are fit for Baptiſm, that know nothing of it, or care nothing for it. But if its Qualifications
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172831:13"/>for Baptiſm be increaſed by it, tell us by what means? Truly for ought I know, you may even intend as little by it when you ſay they are capable of <hi>Proſelytiſm,</hi> than as if you had told us they are capable of <hi>Sleeping.</hi> But to enlarge no farther upon this, I ſhall only ſay that it's a very plain Caſe, that this Text will do no Service for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe there is not one Word of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> ſpoke of in the Text, tho recorded by three Evangeliſts; and it is not likely that a Text that makes nothing for <hi>any Body</hi>'s Baptiſm, ſhould make any thing for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe our <hi>Saviour</hi> makes no improvement of ſuch an Argument as this to your purpoſe; and yet doubtleſs he knew as much of their <hi>Proſelytiſm</hi> as you can pretend to know: And if he did not, pray, why ſhould you? He ſaw nothing in it for their <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> I marvel how you came to be ſo ſtrong-ſighted: Yet you are ſo far from being able to prove that Chriſt <hi>baptized</hi> theſe Children, that we are able to prove he baptized them not; as appears, Joh. 4.2. <hi>Jeſus himſelf baptized none.</hi> And if ſo, this Text rather affords an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt Infant-Baptiſm than for it. And if you will not believe me, I ſhall leave you to ſtruggle with Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> about it; who tells us, <hi>The Concluſion would with more probability be derived thus; Chriſt bleſſed Children, and ſo diſmiſſed them, but baptized them not: Therefore Infants are not to be baptized.</hi> Let us ſee, Sirs, when you will be able to give us a better Argument for it, than this is againſt it.</p>
            <p>You tell us you meet with Inſtances of Children that have been ſo young, ſome before they could either go or ſpeak, that have had ſtrange <hi>Exits</hi> into another World: Well, and what then? pray, what's all this to <hi>Infant-Baptiſm?</hi> Certainly, their going out of this World, let it be by what <hi>Exit</hi> it will, can be no Argument for their <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> unleſs you will ſuppoſe that they ought to be baptized after they are <hi>dead,</hi> or elſe in the <hi>next World,</hi> by virtue of their ſtrange Departure out of <hi>this:</hi> For you cannot make uſe of this Argument till you have it, and you cannot have it till you ſee and know their <hi>Exits</hi> into another World; and then you have no ſooner <hi>got it,</hi> but you have <hi>loſt it.</hi> Beſides, you cannot but know, that a thouſand ſuch Stories as theſe are not at all to the Queſtion between us; for the Queſtion in this Caſe between you and your <hi>Antagoniſts,</hi> is not concerning the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Infants,</hi> but rather concerning their <hi>Duty,</hi> if there <hi>is</hi> any ſuch thing in the World; and if there <hi>be,</hi> whether <hi>Baptiſm</hi> be any part of it: If there <hi>be</hi> not, then we think we may ſafely conclude <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> to be no Duty. For we
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172831:13"/>ſay, all the true Subjects of Baptiſm are bound in <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> to yield <hi>Obedience</hi> to God in that Ordinance, which <hi>Infants</hi> cannot do, neither is it required of them, neither do they loſe any Priviledg, or one jot of God's Favour through the want of it. But if you ſay the Duty lies not upon the <hi>Infants,</hi> but upon the <hi>Parents;</hi> then if you would defend this Argument, you are bound to prove that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires all ſuch Parents, whoſe Children make ſuch <hi>Exits</hi> at their Death, to <hi>baptize</hi> their dead <hi>Children;</hi> for they cannot come at this Argument ſooner: But as for all other <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerns them not. And yet in the ſtrength of this <hi>miſerable</hi> Argument, you can <hi>valiantly</hi> trample upon your <hi>Antagoniſts,</hi> and boldly tell the World, that you may (by virtue of this rare Argument) <hi>with all the Indignation imaginable, explode that uncharitable Poſition of the Anabaptiſts, that ſay, Children have no more Right to Baptiſm than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Creatures:</hi> When, alas! this Poſition, let it be what it will, appears to be not one jot <hi>better</hi> or <hi>worſe,</hi> either for your <hi>Indignation,</hi> or for the <hi>Argument</hi> from whence it flows. However, Sirs, we only ſay <hi>Infants</hi> have no Right to <hi>Baptiſm</hi> by God's Appointment, for God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires no ſuch thing of them, nor from them: if you ſay they have, for my part I ſhould be very well pleaſed to ſee you able to prove it: But if you cannot prove it, you ought to be as well pleaſed to let it be otherwiſe, without reflecting upon any Body. Now, indeed, there is a Conſequential Truth in it, which I know you love dearly to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, if by any means you may render us obnoxious to the Hatred and Diſpleaſure of the Fooliſh. For I confeſs, it cannot properly be ſaid that they that have <hi>no</hi> Right at all to a thing, can have <hi>any more</hi> Right to that thing, than any <hi>other</hi> thing that has likewiſe no Right to the ſame. And yet we have not the leaſt uncharitableneſs in our Breaſts or Thoughts againſt <hi>Infants;</hi> for we ſay they are not one tittle the worſe for having no Right to Baptiſm, nor any thing the leſs in the <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Favour</hi> of God <hi>without it:</hi> It only argues that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their reach and capacity; and as it is ſo, God neither requires nor expects they ſhould be concern'd about it. And pray, Sirs, what's that to <hi>you,</hi> or to <hi>me</hi> either, if it be ſo? If this be the Caſe, who is it you quarrel with? Now, Sirs, 'tis you <hi>Pedo-Baptiſts</hi> rather that are ſo uncharitable toward poor <hi>Infants,</hi> that unleſs you may have your own Wills, and have them <hi>baptiz'd</hi> (as you miſcal it) not only whether they themſelves will or no, but even whether God will or no, you preſently grow ſo <hi>Surly</hi> and <hi>Ill-condition'd</hi> towards poor harmleſs <hi>Babes,</hi> that there's ſcarce one in forty of you can afford them a good
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172831:14"/>word; and not only ſo, but condemn, cenſure and ſentence them far beyond what they dare pretend to do by any <hi>unreaſonable Creature.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> you forget that you your ſelves are guilty of the ſelf-ſame Crime, or at leaſt a Crime of the ſame Nature, which you here pretend with ſo much <hi>Indignation</hi> to <hi>explode:</hi> And why may not we reflect upon you, as well as you upon us, by telling you, That <hi>we may with all the Indignation imaginable explode that uncharitable Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Pedo-Baptiſts, that ſay Infants have no more Right to the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per than unreaſonable Creatures?</hi> Is not this altogether as ſayable from <hi>your</hi> practice, as the other is from <hi>theirs?</hi> and is not this as <hi>bad</hi> and as <hi>uncharitable</hi> a Poſition as the other? What's the Matter, Sirs, that you ſeem to be ſo <hi>quick-ſighted</hi> abroad, and ſo very <hi>blind</hi> at home?</p>
            <p>But above all things, I perceive, I muſt not forget the Inſtance of the <hi>Ruler's Daughter;</hi> for it ſeems there lies ſo much ſtrength in that for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> that it muſt be reckon'd a piece of <hi>Cowardiſe</hi> to evade it. You ſay, you <hi>would ask ſuch Perſons who deny Infants uncapable of Baptiſm, becauſe they can ſhew no actual Sign of it.</hi> By the way, Sirs, I muſt demand of you who are the Perſons you mean here, <hi>that deny Infants to be uncapable of Baptiſm?</hi> Surely you cannot mean the People you call <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> for they plainly ſay, that Infants <hi>are</hi> uncapable of <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> and if any will ſay that they can and do give <hi>Actual Signs</hi> and <hi>Demonſtrations</hi> of their Incapacity in that Caſe, I ſhall not reckon it worth my while to contradict them. Here, Sirs, you ſeem to be ſo eager in the diſcharge of this <hi>Mortar-piece,</hi> that you have miſerably <hi>over-ſhot</hi> your ſelves, which you it ſeems look'd upon to be ſo formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, that becauſe the <hi>Gentleman</hi> in his <hi>Animadverſions</hi> thought it had been <hi>empty,</hi> and ſo paſſed it by as a <hi>uſeleſs</hi> thing; you reckon it was becauſe he was <hi>afraid</hi> to come near it. Well, however, ſome Body it is you have a mind to ask what they think of the <hi>Ruler's Daughter?</hi> Our <hi>Saviour,</hi> ſay you, <hi>bid him only believe, and it ſhould be done.</hi> Would not any now be ready to think, that ſurely this muſt be ſome plain Inſtance of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm?</hi> when they that are ſuppos'd to deny it are ſo briskly and cloſely call'd upon to <hi>tell</hi> their <hi>Thoughts</hi> of ſuch a <hi>particular</hi> Inſtance, that is in ſhort, without any Paraphraſe, brought to <hi>confute</hi> them. Certainly if it chance to prove a Story of <hi>another</hi> Nature, and relate to <hi>another</hi> thing, and not at all to <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> our <hi>Gentlemen</hi> then muſt needs be ſtrangely <hi>impertinent,</hi> and deſerve to be corrected in their Imperious Confidence. Now let any body, for tryal-ſake, but read the Story as it's recorded by three Evangeliſts, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. <hi>Mark</hi> 5. and <hi>Luke</hi> 8. and they will find it to be only a Story, wherein is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172831:14"/>an excellent Relation of our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Power and Compaſſion towards poor Mortals, manifeſted in reſtoring a <hi>young Damſel</hi> to Life and Health, even when ſhe was ſuppoſed to have been dead. And now, Sirs, my <hi>Thoughts</hi> of the <hi>Ruler's Daughter,</hi> is, that ſhe was recover'd by our <hi>Saviour</hi> from a very dangerous Diſtemper, and given as it were again to her Father, as a freſh token of our Saviour's Kindneſs to him. And for you only to ſay (as you do in your Second Paper) <hi>this ſhews that believing Parents Faith avail for their Children.</hi> What is it you talk of? you muſt needs know 'tis nothing to your purpoſe: For, in the Senſe of this Text, who ever deny'd it? We deny not, but the Father's Faith, Humility and Love to Chriſt <hi>might</hi> and <hi>did</hi> greatly avail herein, as to the <hi>Recovery</hi> and <hi>Reſtoration</hi> of his <hi>Daughter:</hi> but ſtill we deny, that ſhe immediately became a true and proper Subject of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> by her <hi>Father's</hi> Faith; there is not the leaſt Shadow of ſuch an <hi>availment</hi> in the Text: Our Saviour doth not ſay, <hi>believe,</hi> and thy Daughter ſhall be <hi>baptized,</hi> nor any thing tending thereunto. And, Sirs, you ought to know, that if you plead for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> upon the <hi>Parents Faith,</hi> nothing ſhort of ſuch a-like Inſtance will, or can, do your Buſineſs: You know very well, that whether a good Man's Faith, and pious Endeavours, may or may not be <hi>available,</hi> in the behalf of a <hi>Child,</hi> a <hi>Wife,</hi> a <hi>Servant,</hi> a <hi>Neighbour,</hi> a <hi>Friend,</hi> yea or an <hi>Enemy</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in ſome reſpects, is no part of the Queſtion in Debate. And if you ſhould affirm that it may, and ſometimes is available, who do you think will be your Enemy therein? Now for you <hi>to clap your Wings,</hi> as it were, and <hi>crow</hi> as if you had got ſome famous <hi>Victory,</hi> by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging this Piece, when you know you have not ſo much as <hi>kill'd</hi> a <hi>Flea</hi> in your Enemies Quarters; What ſtrange Men are you? Pray, Sirs, why were you not ſo publick-ſpirited as to bring in the <hi>Centurion's</hi> Servant to take his ſhare of Right to <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> out of the common ſtock of <hi>ſecond-hand Faith?</hi> Was not his <hi>Maſter's</hi> Faith as <hi>available</hi> to him, as the <hi>Ruler's</hi> was to his <hi>Daughter?</hi> Pray read the Story in <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. and <hi>Luke</hi> 7. and you may eaſily perceive it was ſo. Now what Rule is this for you to baptize any of your <hi>Servants,</hi> whether they <hi>believe</hi> or not <hi>believe,</hi> meerly becauſe <hi>you your ſelves</hi> believe, and plead their Right to <hi>Baptiſm</hi> by virtue of <hi>your</hi> Faith? Beſides, If this Argument were good for the purpoſe you bring it, I cannot imagine who muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from Baptiſm: For it will not only take in any ungodly Perſon whatſoever, upon whoſe account a godly Man may, in ſome reſpects, prevail with God; but it will take in whole Cities of ungodly Men by the Lump, and make them all immediately true Subjects of Baptiſm,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172831:15"/>without any Change or Alteration at all in themſelves. For you know God, upon <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Requeſt, offer'd to ſpare the whole City of <hi>Sodom,</hi> if there could have been but <hi>Ten</hi> Righteous Perſons found in it: And it had certainly been ſav'd from that fearful and amazing Ruin and Deſtruction that befel it, if only <hi>Ten</hi> had been there found. Now the <hi>Argument</hi> is the ſame in its <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Conſequence,</hi> tho they were not found as if they had been found; and if they had been there found, pray tell us what you would have to be the Conſequence of your Argument, concerning all the reſt of the Inhabitants? And if God ſhould ſhew any Kindneſs to any City, Place or Kingdom <hi>now a-days,</hi> upon the account of the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> of ſome Righteous Perſons, as there's no doubt but he doth, Would not this Argument turn all the Inhabitants immediately into Subjects of Baptiſm? And who knows but in your next you may improve it to the utmoſt; and why not? For it is of the ſame Stamp with the <hi>Ruler's Daughter:</hi> And we know you are <hi>Valiant,</hi> and dare venture upon very great Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings.</p>
            <p>You likewiſe tell us, That <hi>'tis a great Weakneſs to believe Children not baptized from the example of the Jaylor.</hi> Indeed, Sirs, I rather think 'tis a <hi>greater</hi> Weakneſs for any to believe they <hi>were:</hi> If by that am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous Term, <hi>Children,</hi> you mean little <hi>Infants,</hi> ſuch as you frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>baptize:</hi> And 'tis not your <hi>Syriac Latiniz'd</hi> that will help you at this turn. For pray, Sirs, what great Diſcovery have you made by going to <hi>Syria,</hi> and there hearing of the <hi>Jaylor's Sons?</hi> You need not have taken that pains, (eſpecially ſince 'tis to no purpoſe) for we can freely grant you, without putting you to ſtruggle for it, that the <hi>Jaylor</hi> might have ſeveral <hi>Sons,</hi> yea and <hi>Daughters</hi> too: And if he had had ten <hi>Sons,</hi> and as many <hi>Daughters,</hi> I readily acknowledg that in all probability they were <hi>all</hi> baptiz'd. I will not ſo much as ſuppoſe that any of his <hi>Houſe,</hi> let them be <hi>Sons</hi> or <hi>Daughters,</hi> or <hi>Servants,</hi> or what elſe you pleaſe, were here exempted from being <hi>baptized.</hi> But yet ſtill, Sirs, you cannot chuſe but know (or elſe you muſt be horribly ignorant) that all this does you no Service at all for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm;</hi> you are ſtill but where you were, you have gain'd nothing at all by this <hi>Syriac</hi> Bargain, tho you ſeem as great upon it, as if you had been at ſome profitable Market: For ſurely nothing can be more evident, than that <hi>all</hi> that were here baptized in, or of, the <hi>Jaylor's Houſe,</hi> were <hi>grown</hi> Perſons, and famous <hi>Converts,</hi> not only <hi>Actual,</hi> but <hi>Active, Lively,</hi> and <hi>Spiritous Believers.</hi> For how plainly does the Text tell us that <hi>they ſpake the Word of the Lord to the Jaylor, and to all that were in his Houſe.</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:172831:15"/>Here it ſeems <hi>teaching</hi> went before <hi>baptizing,</hi> however it came about. But do we hear of any <hi>Infants</hi> yet? Altho we ſhould ſuppoſe them all to be <hi>Sons,</hi> which is not probable, for there might be <hi>Daughters</hi> as well as <hi>Sons,</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> as well as either: But not an <hi>Infant</hi> amongſt them all. And when he and all his were baptized, he brings his welcome Priſoners into his Houſe, and like a good Chriſtian, ſet Meat before them, <hi>and rejoyced, believing in God, with all his Houſe.</hi> Suppoſe it were <hi>all the Sons</hi> of his Houſe ſtill, it's the ſame thing, it's plain they were <hi>All</hi> Believers, let them be whoſe <hi>Sons</hi> they will. What a ſtrange thing it is, that our <hi>Gentlemen</hi> cannot underſtand them to be <hi>Believers,</hi> meerly becauſe it's thought they might be <hi>Sons:</hi> When alas! the <hi>Jaylor</hi> himſelf, no doubt, had a <hi>Father,</hi> and was certainly Some-body's <hi>Son.</hi> Now it ſeems it lies within the reach of our <hi>Gentlemens</hi> Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that the <hi>Jaylor</hi> himſelf might be a <hi>Believer,</hi> but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think that his <hi>Sons</hi> ſhould be ſuch: Pray, Sirs, why might not the <hi>Jaylor's Sons,</hi> if he had any, be <hi>Believers</hi> as well as their <hi>Grand-Father's</hi> Son? 'Tis true any Body would be ready to think they might, and not only ſo, but that in reality they were ſo too. But then this quite ſpoils our <hi>Gentlemens</hi> Buſineſs, for they muſt have <hi>Infants,</hi> or they die. And therefore, rather than they will admit of this, they'l ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to tell you, <hi>'tis Nonſenſe to urge from the conſequent Text, that thoſe which were baptized, glorifyed and praiſed God, which Children could not do:</hi> And that which proves it Nonſenſe, is, becauſe <hi>it only means ſuch as were capable of doing it. Gentlemen,</hi> 'tis very true; you are now in the Right, 'tis only meant of ſuch as were <hi>capable</hi> of doing it: But then 'tis <hi>as</hi> true, that it means <hi>all</hi> of the <hi>Jaylor's Houſe</hi> that were <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized;</hi> for it's certain that <hi>all</hi> that were here baptized, were <hi>capable</hi> of ſo doing, and <hi>did</hi> ſo do. If I be ſo <hi>honeſt</hi> as to grant what you ſay in the former, I hope you will not be ſo <hi>diſhoneſt</hi> as to deny what I and the Text both ſay in the latter: For it's a plain Caſe, that there were <hi>no more</hi> baptized of the <hi>Jaylor's Houſe</hi> than what were firſt Converted by the preaching of the <hi>Word of the Lord;</hi> and glorifyed God in the ſtrength of their Faith: But <hi>Infants</hi> are not capable of this: <hi>Ergo,</hi> All your <hi>Infants</hi> are loſt.</p>
            <p>There's one <hi>profound</hi> Obſervation more which you make hereabouts, which I ſhall a little Remark, and ſo proceed to ſomething elſe. <hi>At their Rate,</hi> ſay you, <hi>we ſhall have all the Children of Anabaptiſts ſtarved: For 'tis ſaid, he that will not work, let him not eat: But Children muſt eat, tho not capable of working,</hi> &amp;c. But why I beſeech you at <hi>their</hi> Rate, any more than at <hi>your</hi> Rate? What is it that makes <hi>them</hi> ſo guilty in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172831:16"/>this <hi>ſad</hi> ſuppoſed <hi>Murder</hi> any more than <hi>your ſelves?</hi> You have not in any meaſure made it appear, how <hi>they</hi> ſtand chargeable with ſuch a <hi>Crime,</hi> whilſt <hi>your ſelves</hi> remain Innocent: I wiſh you had attempted it, for aſſuredly, Sirs, ſuch a <hi>Charge</hi> requires a <hi>Demonſtration.</hi> But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as many ignorant People will be apt to take it for granted, meerly becauſe you tell them ſo, tho they know no more why than a Poſt: I ſhall gueſs at your meaning as well as I can, and either <hi>clear</hi> the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> of this frightful Suggeſtion, or elſe bring <hi>you</hi> in <hi>guilty</hi> along with them. Now, I hope, we may take this Propoſition for granted without any more a-do; Namely, that <hi>you</hi> are not at all guilty of this ſtrange <hi>Plot</hi> againſt all the <hi>Infants in the World.</hi> Now if I can but make it appear, that if <hi>you</hi> be Innocent, <hi>they</hi> cannot be Guilty; or if <hi>they</hi> be Guilty, <hi>you</hi> cannot be Innocent: I hope you will be willing to diſmiſs them without Damage. Your meaning then certainly, I think, muſt be to this purpoſe; That foraſmuch as the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> ſay that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> are not to be <hi>baptized,</hi> becauſe not capable of <hi>believing;</hi> They may as well, and do in effect ſay, that <hi>Infants</hi> muſt not <hi>eat,</hi> becauſe not capable of <hi>working;</hi> for tho <hi>Faith</hi> is required of <hi>grown</hi> Perſons in order to <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> ſo is <hi>Working</hi> required of <hi>them</hi> in order to <hi>Eating.</hi> But now <hi>Infants</hi> may either be <hi>baptized</hi> without <hi>believing,</hi> or elſe it will follow that they may not <hi>eat</hi> without <hi>working.</hi> Herein I reckon I have done you the utmoſt Juſtice imaginable, in ſtating your Proof to the full, which you ought to have done your ſelves; but perhaps you durſt not, leſt your Folly ſhould have been the more eaſily diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. Now, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I intend to <hi>join Iſſue</hi> with you, and ſee what Concluſion we can bring it to. Sirs, why may not I as well conclude, that becauſe you ſay that <hi>Infants</hi> are not to be admitted to the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> becauſe not capable of <hi>Self-Examination,</hi> or <hi>diſcerning the Lord's Body;</hi> you may as well ſay that <hi>Infants</hi> muſt not <hi>eat,</hi> becauſe not capable of <hi>working:</hi> For tho <hi>Self-Examination &amp;c.</hi> is required of <hi>grown</hi> Perſons, as previous to the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> and <hi>working</hi> required of them in order to <hi>eating;</hi> But as for <hi>Infants</hi> they muſt either be admitted to the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> without <hi>Self-Examination,</hi> or elſe it will follow that they muſt not <hi>eat</hi> without <hi>working:</hi> And therefore at <hi>your</hi> Rate all your Children muſt be <hi>ſtarv'd,</hi> and not only ſo, <hi>but the Race of all Chriſtians, nay of the whole World, muſt ſoon be extirpated,</hi> as you very boldly tell us in your Paper. Now, Sirs, your Charge is very fairly return'd upon your ſelves; What ſay you, <hi>Guilty</hi> or <hi>not Guilty?</hi> To ſuppoſe you will plead <hi>Guilty</hi> here, would be little leſs than to commit <hi>Sacriledg;</hi> yet if you ſay <hi>Not Guilty,</hi> you do in ſo ſaying fully acquit your <hi>Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſts:</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:172831:16"/>For now it appears, that if you be <hi>Innocent,</hi> they cannot be <hi>Guilty:</hi> And ſo I hope this dreadful <hi>Tattle</hi> of <hi>ſtarving Infants</hi> is blown over, and come to nothing. Yet, Sirs, I think you ought to take ſome <hi>blame</hi> and <hi>ſhame</hi> too, to your ſelves, for being ſo mighty willing to expoſe and condemn your Neighbour for nothing. I ſhall only ſay thus much more for the preſent to this matter, and ſo leave it, <hi>viz.</hi> If you had but clearly prov'd that God has given <hi>you</hi> the like Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Authority to <hi>baptize</hi> Children in their <hi>Infancy,</hi> as he hath done to <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Mothers</hi> to <hi>feed</hi> them in their <hi>Infancy,</hi> you had then ſaid ſomething to the purpoſe; otherwiſe you had far better have ſaid nothing.</p>
            <p>But the Text ſaith, Act. 2.39. <hi>The Promiſe is to you, and to your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> Well, Sirs, it doth ſo: But how comes this Text to be any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to your purpoſe for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm?</hi> eſpecially, unleſs you were able to prove, that by <hi>Children</hi> here is undoubtedly meant <hi>Infants,</hi> which I doubt you will find ſuch a Task, as you will hardly ever live to finiſh: What, Sirs, do you take it for granted that <hi>Infants</hi> muſt here be underſtood, meerly becauſe you find the Word <hi>children</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Text? What ſtrange Reaſoning is this? Is this one of your <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> and <hi>unavoidable</hi> Conſequences you talk of in your Paper? Why may you not as well conclude, that becauſe the Text tells us, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 22. That the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Reuben</hi> and the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Gad</hi> built them an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar:</hi> Ergo, The <hi>Infants</hi> of <hi>Reuben</hi> and <hi>Gad</hi> were <hi>Maſons</hi> and <hi>Stone-Cutters.</hi> And becauſe it's ſaid concerning the Vertuous Woman, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.28. <hi>Her Children riſe up and call her Bleſſed:</hi> Therefore her <hi>Infants of eight Days</hi> old did ſo. And our Saviour ſaith of <hi>Jeruſalem, How often would I have gather'd thy Children together, as a Hen gathereth her Chickens under her Wings, and ye would not?</hi> Can it rationally be ſuppoſed that our Saviour here means <hi>Infants</hi> in the Cradle? And yet a little Conſideration will make you capable of diſcerning that <hi>Infants</hi> are not more excluded by <hi>theſe Texts,</hi> than they are by <hi>this Text</hi> now in Hand. For if <hi>Infants</hi> are here intended, then the Promiſe here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, let it be what Promiſe it will, is not <hi>Conditional,</hi> but muſt be <hi>Abſolute:</hi> But the Promiſe here ſpoken of is not <hi>abſolute,</hi> but <hi>conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal:</hi> Ergo, <hi>&amp;c. Repentance</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is here plainly requir'd, as the <hi>Means</hi> or <hi>Condition</hi> leading to the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> unto which the <hi>Promiſe</hi> is annexed; without which the <hi>Promiſe</hi> is not to be claim'd. And the <hi>Promiſe</hi> is here mention'd as a <hi>Motive</hi> or <hi>Encouragement</hi> to perform the <hi>Duties</hi> or <hi>Condition</hi> requir'd. And who is it, that in the reading the Text is not able to diſcern this? If you were not ſtrangely <hi>biaſſed,</hi> or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:172831:17"/>devoted to an Error, methinks you might eaſily perceive, that by <hi>you and your Children</hi> in this Text, is meant the <hi>Jews and their Poſterity</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, as they ſhould come to cloſe with this Doctrine now taught them: Wherein they are all encourag'd to fall in with Chriſt upon the Terms of the Goſpel, for Remiſſion of Sins and Salvation, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their great and unparallel'd Wickedneſs, in killing the <hi>Lord of Life,</hi> and imprecating that dreadful <hi>Curſe</hi> upon themſelves, and their <hi>Children,</hi> or <hi>Poſterity,</hi> the cutting Senſe whereof, now upon their Hearts, might have been apt to have driven them to Deſpair, had it not been for <hi>Peter</hi>'s Cordial: Wherefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> gives them to underſtand that God would not be ſo ſevere as to take ſuch Advantage thereby, but that upon their hearty Repentance, and Submiſſion to the Terms of Salvation required in the Goſpel, <hi>they</hi> and their <hi>Children,</hi> or <hi>Poſterity</hi> after them, upon the <hi>ſame Terms,</hi> ſhould certainly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to Mercy. All that I ſhall ſay more to this at preſent, ſhall be only to recommend to you the Sayings of two eminent <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Doctors, in Reference to this Text and Matter, Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Taylor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any,</hi> ſaith Dr. <hi>Hammond, have made uſe of that unconcludent Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, I have nothing to ſay in defence of them: I think,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Practice is founded upon better Baſis than ſo; and the word</hi> Children <hi>there, is really the Poſterity of the Jews, and not particularly their Infant Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> upon this Scripture, ſaith; <hi>That the words menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd in St.</hi> Peter<hi>'s Sermon, are interpreted upon a weak Miſtake: The Promiſe is to you and your Children, therefore Infants are actually receptive of it, in that Capacity; that's the Argument: but the Reaſon of it is not yet diſcover'd, nor ever will: for to you, and your Children, is to you and your Poſterity: to you and your Children, when they are of the ſame Capacity, in which you are receptive of the Promiſe: But he that, whenever the word Children is uſed in Scripture, ſhall by Children underſtand Infants, muſt needs believe, that in all</hi> Iſrael <hi>there were no Men; but all were Infants. And if that had been true, it had been the greater Wonder they ſhould overcome the</hi> Anakims, <hi>and beat the King of</hi> Moab; <hi>and march ſo far, and diſcourſe ſo well, for they were all called the Children of</hi> Iſrael. Now, Gentlemen, I leave you to your liberty, whether you will, in this caſe, contend further, or ſubmit.</p>
            <p>But you ſay, <hi>Children are in the Covenant,</hi> and <hi>they are holy, and of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. I might here juſtly enquire, what you mean by <hi>Infants</hi> being in the <hi>Covenant;</hi> and whether you mean
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172831:17"/>
               <hi>all Infants</hi> in the World, or but ſome; if all, I wiſh you would tell us ſo; if but ſome, then which are they? or whether any thing is requir'd of them, or is to be done by them, in order to their getting into the <hi>Covenant?</hi> if any thing, what? if nothing, how came they in more than others? or whether it is their <hi>Vertue</hi> to be <hi>in,</hi> and the <hi>Sin</hi> of others to be <hi>out?</hi> or whether there is any <hi>difference</hi> in the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity</hi> of thoſe that are <hi>in,</hi> and thoſe that are <hi>out?</hi> Is their Wiſdom, Knowledg, Judgment and Underſtanding, Increas'd by it, or not? if you ſay it is, you muſt make it manifeſt: but if not, then there is <hi>no difference</hi> betwixt them and <hi>others,</hi> in reſpect of their <hi>Fitneſs</hi> for <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay, I might enlarge and inſiſt upon ſeveral things of this kind: Which I confeſs, I could be glad to be reſolv'd in: But for the preſent I ſhall not here inſiſt, but ſhall rather take you at all Adventures; and mean what you pleaſe by all theſe Allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew you, that there is <hi>nothing at all</hi> in them for <hi>your purpoſe.</hi> For what if I grant you all you ſay in theſe caſes, that <hi>Infants</hi> are in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>Holy,</hi> and <hi>ſuch as ſhall be ſaved,</hi> &amp;c. what then? if you infer, that <hi>then,</hi> or <hi>therefore,</hi> they ought to be <hi>baptis'd,</hi> I deny that Conſequence: for by this Rule, <hi>Moſes</hi> might have <hi>baptis'd Infants</hi> as well as you, if a <hi>bare</hi> being in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> &amp;c. were ſufficient to warrant the Practice: however, Sirs, he might have <hi>circumcis'd</hi> them, the <hi>firſt, ſecond,</hi> or <hi>third</hi> Day after they were born, as well as to have ſtaid till the <hi>eighth Day:</hi> for certainly, they were as <hi>holy,</hi> and as much <hi>in the Covenant,</hi> and as <hi>fit for the Kingdom of Heaven</hi> the <hi>firſt</hi> or <hi>ſecond</hi> Day, as they were the <hi>eighth:</hi> and what's the reaſon think you that he did not? He might alſo have <hi>circumcis'd Females,</hi> if this had been good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, for there's no doubt to be made, but <hi>they</hi> were <hi>holy,</hi> and in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>ſuch as ſhould be ſaved,</hi> as well as the <hi>Males.</hi> But if he had done ſo, would he not (think you) have been a <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor</hi> rather than a <hi>faithful Servant?</hi> Yet he might have taken up <hi>your Plea,</hi> and defended himſelf altogether as well as you do or can, in the buſineſs of <hi>Infant-baptiſm:</hi> but it's a plain caſe, he did not <hi>like</hi> this <hi>Argument.</hi> But, Sirs, you ought to remember that the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure</hi> of God, ought in a ſpecial manner to be heeded in all ſuch Caſes: for it is the Command of God that gives Life and Being to all Duty, <hi>without which,</hi> all your Allegations are in vain: <hi>with which,</hi> we ſhould gladly ceaſe to contend; and that's the reaſon why <hi>Infants</hi> were <hi>circumcis'd</hi> preciſely upon the <hi>eighth Day,</hi> either before, or after, would certainly have incurr'd Diſpleaſure. And this was
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172831:18"/>that which kept <hi>Females</hi> from <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> tho <hi>holy</hi> and in <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> as well as <hi>Males.</hi> Nay, if Chriſt had not commanded <hi>Believers</hi> to be <hi>baptis'd,</hi> their being <hi>Believers</hi> would not have <hi>juſtified</hi> the Practice, neither will it now <hi>juſtify</hi> any other Practice that he never <hi>commanded</hi> or <hi>appointed</hi> to be done. Beſides, Sirs, do you not herein <hi>ſin,</hi> becauſe <hi>Grace</hi> abounds? for is God ſo good and gracious, as to place our <hi>Infants</hi> in <hi>Covenant</hi> with himſelf, muſt we therefore take the holy Name of God in vain, and ſprinkle Water upon their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as if we ſuppos'd the <hi>Covenant</hi> worth nothing, unleſs we confirm it with our own <hi>Inventions,</hi> and clap a <hi>Seal</hi> to it of our <hi>own making,</hi> without any <hi>order</hi> from him ſo to do? Sirs, if <hi>Infants</hi> be in <hi>Covenant,</hi> be content there to let them reſt, without diſturbing or interrupting them in it: be content with that, till you are able to make them ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the <hi>Obligations</hi> that may lie upon them, by virtue thereof to diſcharge Duty towards God.</p>
            <p>I have only two Demands to make, and then I ſhall leave this to Conſideration:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Pray, Sirs, tell us, do you think <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did not know as much of this Nature, concerning <hi>Infants,</hi> as you do? do you think they were not as well acquainted with their being <hi>holy</hi> and in the <hi>Covenant, and ſuch as ſhould be ſav'd,</hi> as you are? I hope, as Learned as you are, you will hardly venture to ſay they did not: yet where did <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or any of his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> give either Command or Permiſſion, to any Body, to <hi>baptiſe</hi> their <hi>Infants</hi> upon any of <hi>theſe</hi> accounts? Where is thee the leaſt Sign or Shadow of ſuch a thing, in all the New-Teſtament? If you know of any, pray produce it, and let us ſee it, that we may read and underſtand ſuch a thing as well as your ſelves; and in ſo doing, the Controverſy would ſoon be ended: but if there be no ſuch things ſignify? if you ſhould argue and write for three ſeven Years together, what is it all worth, unleſs you bring Scripture-warrant for what you affirm and practiſe?</p>
            <p>My ſecond Demand upon this account, is as followeth: Suppoſing all theſe things to be unqueſtionably true that you talk of; that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> are in the <hi>Covenant, holy,</hi> and <hi>ſuch as ſhall be ſaved,</hi> and what you pleaſe of that kind: How comes this to intitle them any more to <hi>Baptiſm</hi> than it doth to the <hi>Lord's-Supper?</hi> What's the reaſon, (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you) you do not receive them to the <hi>Lord's Table</hi> upon theſe Accounts, as well as admit them to <hi>Baptiſm?</hi> Are you able to give us an <hi>Inſtance</hi> in all the New-Teſtament of any that were accepted as <hi>fit</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:172831:18"/>Subjects of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and at the ſame time, as ſuch, reckon'd and known to be <hi>unfit</hi> for, and <hi>uncapable</hi> of the Communion of Saints in the <hi>Supper of the Lord?</hi> I marvel, Sirs, what you make of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> that you ſhould think <hi>Infants</hi> ſo fitly and fully qualify'd for that, and yet dare not venture to plead, either <hi>Right,</hi> or <hi>Obligation</hi> to any other Goſpel-duty: Is not <hi>Baptiſm</hi> a <hi>Goſpel-requirement</hi> as well as the <hi>Lord's Supper?</hi> a Command of Chriſt, an Ordinance of Heaven, and part of that Service and Obedience which Chriſtians owe to God, in and under the Goſpel? And do you think it ought not to be done with more Knowledg, Judgment and Reverence, than <hi>Infants of ſeven Days old</hi> are capable of? What <hi>Subjection,</hi> or <hi>Obedience</hi> to God, is there, or can there be, in a <hi>little Infant</hi> in the performance of that which you call its Baptiſm, when it knows nothing at all of the thing <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,</hi> nor of the <hi>Law-giver commanding,</hi> nor any reaſon in the World why it ſhould, or ſhould not ſubmit; neither is it capable of thinking either well, or ill, concerning any thing relating thereunto? How then can it be done as a <hi>Duty,</hi> in <hi>Obedience</hi> to Chriſt, as the anſwer of a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> towards God, when the Subject knows nothing of theſe things, and is altogether <hi>uncapable</hi> of the leaſt <hi>motive</hi> to Subjection? But if you ſay, <hi>Infants</hi> muſt notwithſtanding all this, be admitted to <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> certainly you muſt needs wrong them greatly, in debarring them from the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi> Gentlemen, theſe things deſerves to be well conſider'd; and then take <hi>Advice,</hi> and ſpeak your Minds.</p>
            <p>As to what you ſay about <hi>univerſal conſent of Churches,</hi> and <hi>Antiquity</hi> for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> I ſhall not ſo much as concern my ſelf to enquire after the Truth or Falſhood of the matter; becauſe, let it be true or falſe, all the while it is <hi>Scriptureleſs,</hi> there is not the weight of a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in it: It neither <hi>hurts us,</hi> nor <hi>helps you,</hi> in this Caſe. For what does all the <hi>Conſent</hi> you talk of ſignify, unleſs you can clearly prove the thing <hi>conſented</hi> to, to be Truth without it? And if you can, then you have no need of its help; but if you cannot, it has no help for you; for it is not the greateſt <hi>Conſent</hi> imaginable that can make a <hi>Falſhood</hi> Truth: It muſt either be <hi>Truth</hi> previous to that <hi>Conſent,</hi> or elſe it remains a <hi>Falſhood</hi> notwithſtanding that <hi>Conſent:</hi> The <hi>Conſent</hi> it ſelf can be no Argument to prove it <hi>Truth.</hi> So that all that appears from this Argument, if all that you ſay were ſuppos'd to be unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably true, is only this, That <hi>a great many People a great while agoe</hi> held <hi>Infant-Baptiſm;</hi> but whether they did well or ill, in ſo doing, ſtill remains the Queſtion, as much as ever: And if it want the true
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:172831:19"/>
               <hi>Primitive</hi> Mark of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> let it be as <hi>old</hi> as it will, 'tis never the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for that, but indeed the worſe; for that only ſerves to prove it an <hi>old over-grown</hi> Error. As <hi>old</hi> as it is, it is not <hi>old</hi> enough to be <hi>Truth,</hi> becauſe <hi>from the beginning it was not ſo.</hi> 'Tis in vain to talk of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> all the while you want the true ground thereof; for if that be wanting, all your talk of <hi>Antiquity</hi> is ſo far from being an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for it, that it is clearly an Argument againſt it: For if it be <hi>very old,</hi> and of a <hi>long ſtanding,</hi> and yet not <hi>old</hi> enough to be <hi>Truth,</hi> it's high time for us, even for that Reaſon, to reject and explode it with Indignation. As a Learned <hi>Church of England Doctor</hi> well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves and directs, ſpeaking of <hi>old Popiſh</hi> Pretenſions, <hi>When they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>their Revelations, or teach for Doctrines of God the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of Men; we muſt ask them every one how they read in the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: We may not draw out of their Ditches, be the Current never ſo long, whilſt we have Waters of our own of a nobler taſte, which we can eaſily trace back to the Chryſtal Spring,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The next Queſtion you undertake to Anſwer, is, <hi>Whether Infant-Baptiſm is to be found in Scripture?</hi> Your Anſwer is <hi>not expreſly in the Letter, but from neceſſary and unavoidable Conſequences,</hi> as, ſay you, <hi>we have already ſhewn,</hi> &amp;c. Now, Gentlemen, if the latter part of your Anſwer here were but as true as the former is, I ſhould very readily give you the Caſe, and Diſpute no more; for I am clearly of the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that whatſoever is truly prov'd by <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>unavoidable</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences from <hi>Scripture,</hi> is ſufficiently prov'd, as you ſay, to all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intereſted Perſons. But the miſery of it is, we could never yet ſee theſe <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>unavoidable</hi> Conſequences; but your <hi>Conſequences</hi> are all ſo grievous <hi>ſick</hi> of one Diſtemper or another, that all the <hi>Doctors</hi> in Chriſtendom will never be able to make them <hi>ſound:</hi> And this we have pretty well found by your <hi>Conſequences</hi> hitherto produc'd, unto which I refer, having not now time to repeat. Beſides, <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> if it be true, that there is nothing of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> to be found <hi>expreſly in the Letter of the Scripture,</hi> I cannot readily underſtand how you can come by thoſe <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>unavoidable</hi> Conſequences you talk of: for tho it is true you may lay down a Propoſition in ſuch Terms as cannot be proved <hi>verbatim</hi> from Scripture, and yet I confeſs it may be well enough prov'd from very good <hi>Conſequences.</hi> But if there is nothing at all <hi>expreſly</hi> in Scripture about it, not <hi>one Word</hi> in the <hi>Letter</hi> concerning it, I'me afraid you muſt be content to go without thoſe <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>unavoidable</hi> Conſequences. Sirs, will you ſay that there is nothing of the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> or three in one, to be found
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:172831:19"/>
               <hi>expreſly</hi> in the Scripture? Is there nothing expreſly of the God-head of Chriſt, or of his being born of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> to be found in the Scripture? If there is not, for my part I know no Reaſon in the World they ſhould be received for ſuch Great and Orthodox Truths: But if there is, What ſtrange Men are you to talk at this extravagant Rate, as if the Scripture ſpoke nothing expreſly about theſe Matters? And how boldly do you inſinuate and endeavour to make the World believe, that <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> is at leaſt altogether as plain in Scripture, as Chriſt's being born of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> and <hi>that</hi> altogether as dark and as hard to be prov'd from Scripture as <hi>Infant-Baptiſm.</hi> Now, Sirs, this Inſinuation is either true or falſe: If falſe, don't you deſerve to be ſeverely corrected for ſuch Imperious Tricks? But if you ſtand by it, and ſay it is true, How do you think you would come off if we ſhould join Iſſue with you about it, and bring the matter to a Tryal? But I confeſs I have been ſo large hitherto, beyond my firſt Thoughts or Intentions, that I ſhall ſay no more to this at preſent, and not much to what remains.</p>
            <p>There is no leſs than three Queſtions following which you undertake to anſwer, which I reckon ſo inconſiderable and inſignificant, both Queſtions and Anſwers, that I count it not worth my while to ſpend one Line about them. I therefore purpoſely omit them (time being precious with me) for the ſake of ſomething elſe which I judg more worthy to be noted; wherefore I wave the <hi>Fourth, Sixth</hi> and <hi>Seventh</hi> Queſtions, and paſs on to the <hi>Eighth,</hi> and ſhall take ſome ſmall notice of the <hi>Fifth,</hi> laſt of all, and ſo draw to a Concluſion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Eighth</hi> and Laſt Queſtion you undertake to anſwer, runs thus: <hi>Whether Children have Faith or no, ſince Faith and Repentance are pre-requiſite to Baptiſm?</hi> To which you anſwer and ſay, <hi>That you have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhew'd that according to the Words of the Commiſſion, Baptizing goes before Teaching: Therefore there is no ſuch pre-requiſiteneſs as ſome dream of,</hi> &amp;c. But, Sirs, I tell you plainly this is a meer idle ſwagger, for you have ſhewed no ſuch matter, but the contrary does moſt evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear; therefore there is a greater <hi>pre-requiſiteneſs</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> than <hi>you dream</hi> of. Why you refer us to <hi>Acts</hi> 9. and tell us <hi>our Saviour was born King of the Jews,</hi> I cannot imagine: I wiſh I did but know your Inference. But you ſay further, <hi>Admit Faith as pre-requiſite to Baptiſm, you could anſwer that Children have Faith</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia, <hi>tho not in</hi> actu viſibili; <hi>as an Artiſt, when he is indiſpos'd or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep is potentially an Artiſt, tho not actually.</hi> Sirs, it's a plain Caſe that you meerly ſpeak what you liſt, not knowing <hi>what you ſay,</hi> nor <hi>whereof
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:172831:20"/>you affirm:</hi> What is it that you may not ſay <hi>Infants have,</hi> and <hi>are,</hi> if this kind of talk be allow'd you for good? Whatſoever you have a mind your <hi>Infants</hi> ſhall <hi>have,</hi> or <hi>be,</hi> put but <hi>potentia</hi> to it, and it's done. What if you had been in the Humour to have told us that <hi>Infants</hi> have the <hi>Greek Tongue</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Oriental Languages,</hi> and are as <hi>good Preachers</hi> as any in the World, <hi>potentia,</hi> tho not <hi>in actu viſibili;</hi> as an <hi>Artiſt</hi> when he is a-ſleep, is <hi>potentially</hi> an <hi>Artiſt</hi> tho not <hi>actually?</hi> Could you have expected that any Body in their Wits ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded you? And why not in <hi>this.</hi> I marvel, as well as in the <hi>other?</hi> Beſides Sirs, what can you mean by Childrens having Faith <hi>potentia?</hi> You do not mean that they do <hi>actually</hi> and <hi>viſibly</hi> believe; no by no means, that is not to be imagin'd. Well, but what then do you mean? For my part I think it is partly the ſame thing, at if you had told us only that they have <hi>Power, Might, Strength</hi> and <hi>Ability</hi> to believe; but yet, whatever the matter is, they <hi>do not</hi> believe: Notwithſtanding this <hi>potency</hi> of believing, they neither do, nor can make any improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it ſo as to do the thing. And if this be true, good now what is it you talk of when you ſay Infants have faith <hi>potentia?</hi> And yet if they have <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Ability</hi> to do it, it muſt needs be their <hi>Sin</hi> if they do it not. So that our <hi>Gentlemen's</hi> great Plea for <hi>Infants</hi> ſeems to prove a very <hi>Fatal Charge</hi> againſt them, for the damning Sin of will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Unbelief muſt needs lye upon them, if they have <hi>Strength, Might</hi> and <hi>Ability</hi> to believe, and make no uſe of it to act accordingly.</p>
            <p>Moreover, What reaſon have you to conclude any Man to be an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> tho but <hi>potentially</hi> ſo, when you ſee him aſleep, if you never ſaw, nor knew any thing at all of his being an <hi>Artiſt</hi> before? if he had been <hi>aſleep</hi> all the <hi>Days</hi> of his <hi>Life,</hi> you would have had ſmall cauſe to have counted him an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> tho you had put the word <hi>potentia</hi> to it. But now <hi>Infants</hi> have (to follow your Simile) been <hi>aſleep</hi> all their <hi>Life-time,</hi> in this caſe: You never, ſo much as ſaw, or knew of a time when they were ſo far <hi>awake,</hi> as to ſhew themſelves <hi>Believers,</hi> as the <hi>Artiſt</hi> was to ſhew himſelf and <hi>Artiſt:</hi> So that as you have no reaſon to conclude any Man to be an Artiſt <hi>potentially</hi> when <hi>aſleep,</hi> that you never knew to be any thing of an <hi>Artiſt</hi> actually, at one time or another before; ſo you have no reaſon to conclude <hi>Infants</hi> Believers <hi>potentially,</hi> unleſs you had ſeen or known them at one time or another to have been <hi>actually</hi> ſuch. So that I think you had as good blot out <hi>potentia</hi> (unleſs you will put it to their <hi>Baptiſm</hi> too); and let your Children reſt without <hi>Actual Baptiſm,</hi> till you can write upon their Faith <hi>Actu viſibili.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:172831:20"/>
            <p>But you ſay, our Saviour is full to the purpoſe, who aſſures us, as you tell us in your Second, <hi>that Children have Faith,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall offend one of theſe little ones, which believe in me,</hi> &amp;c. Sirs, I do plainly confeſs that our Saviour is full to the purpoſe, but not to your purpoſe; for he does aſſure us, that the Perſons here ſpoken of, were ſuch as did really, properly, and <hi>actually believe in him:</hi> he does not ſo much as intimate any thing of their having Faith, <hi>poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> but not in <hi>actu viſibili;</hi> but in down-right terms tells us, they are ſuch as <hi>do believe</hi> in him; which little <hi>Infants,</hi> I think, by your own Confeſſion, cannot do: therefore, little <hi>Infants</hi> not here intended by our Saviour in this Paſſage; but only ſuch as were <hi>converted,</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as little Children,</hi> in Plainneſs of Spirit, Humbleneſs, Innocency, and freedom from Malice. Our Saviour does not only aſſure us, that ſuch ſhall be greateſt in the Kingdom of Heaven; but alſo plainly tell us, that <hi>whoſoever ſhall offend,</hi> or ſcandalize, <hi>one of theſe,</hi> thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, <hi>little ones, which believe in him</hi> ſhall certainly incur great Diſpleaſure from God. And this is eaſily diſcern'd, with a little Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, in reading the Text, and Coherence of the ſame: That after our Saviour had call'd a little Child, and taught his Diſciples how they ſhould be <hi>converted,</hi> and <hi>become as little Children,</hi> and <hi>humble</hi> themſelves as <hi>that little Child;</hi> he under that Conſideration, gives the Denomination of <hi>little ones,</hi> even to <hi>ſuch</hi> as ſhould <hi>ſo learn</hi> and <hi>ſo do,</hi> which did truly <hi>believe</hi> in him, from that <hi>Analogy,</hi> that was and ought to be, between <hi>little Children</hi> and <hi>them:</hi> therefore, whereas you argue thus, or to this purpoſe, <hi>[Theſe little ones which believe in me;] therefore Infants do believe.</hi> I argue the direct contrary from the ſame Text, thus; <hi>Thoſe of whom Chriſt here ſpeak, did really believe in him: but little Infants neither do, nor can believe in chriſt:</hi> Ergo, <hi>Chriſt ſpeaks not here of little Infants.</hi> To prove the Minor here, I thus rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; <hi>Faith in Chriſt, comes by hearing the Word of God underſtandingly: but little Infants cannot hear the Word of God underſtandingly:</hi> Ergo, <hi>Little Infants cannot be Believers in Chriſt.</hi> Again, if little Infants nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>do good</hi> or <hi>evil,</hi> nor ſo much a <hi>know good</hi> or <hi>evil,</hi> then they can neither hear the Word of God underſtandingly, (for if they can, they muſt of neceſſity be capable of <hi>knowing good;</hi>) nor be <hi>Believers in Chriſt,</hi> for if they be, they muſt of neceſſity <hi>do good;</hi> for believing <hi>in Chriſt</hi> is one of the beſt things that can be <hi>done</hi> in the world. But the Scripture it ſelf, beſides Experience, plainly tells us concerning Infants, that they neither <hi>do good,</hi> or <hi>evil;</hi> nor <hi>know good</hi> or <hi>evil:</hi> Ergo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.39. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.14, 15, 16. See the <hi>Aſſembly Annotations</hi> on this
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:172831:21"/>Paſſage of our Saviour; and Reverend <hi>Diodate</hi> on the ſame: See al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo theſe Scriptures, where this Phraſe, <hi>little ones,</hi> or <hi>little Children,</hi> is us'd to grown Believers, and Diſciples of Chriſt; <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.41, 42. <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.5 <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.1, 12, 13, 18, 28. &amp; 3.7, 18. &amp; 4.4. &amp; 5.21.</p>
            <p>Beſides, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> if you muſt and will have little <hi>Infants</hi> here intended, then it muſt and will, of neceſſity, be but a <hi>Proſopopoeia</hi> however; and ſo do you no Service at all, tho we ſhould out of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity give you what you ſo earneſtly beg for.</p>
            <p>A few words to your Anſwer to the fifth Queſtion, and ſo I draw to a Concluſion. The Queſtion is only thus; <hi>Why Sprinkling, and not Dipping?</hi> To which you anſwer and ſay, <hi>Our Church denies not the latter to any one that deſires it; but looks upon it as a clear Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Saviour's deſcending into the Grave, abiding there, and riſing up again; according as the Apoſtle makes uſe of it, when he ſays, we are buried with him in Baptiſm.</hi> Sirs, it's a clear caſe, that <hi>Dipping</hi> or <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering</hi> the Body under Water, was the true <hi>Primitive, Apoſtolical</hi> and <hi>Scriptural</hi> way of <hi>Baptizing:</hi> and you and your Church both, ſeems plainly to be convinc'd of the Truth hereof; by this free and full Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and Acknowledgment which here you make; that it is a <hi>clear Repreſentation of our Saviour's deſcending into the Grave, abiding there, and riſing up again:</hi> and this you deliver, not as a Conceit that may come into a Man's Brains by chance; no, but 'tis very ſeriouſly given us, as a thing by your own Acknowledgment, which is according to Scripture, as the <hi>Apoſtle himſelf makes uſe of it,</hi> when he tells us, <hi>we are buried with him in Baptiſm.</hi> Now, Sirs, ſtand by this, and all's well; but if you will be ſo unfaithful, as to diſſert theſe true primitive Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, you certainly run away from <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Subſtance,</hi> to cloſe with <hi>Falſhood</hi> and <hi>Vanity:</hi> for either this is the mind of God, which you have here ventur'd to give us, or it is not: If it be not, wherefore did you urge it as a thing, not only <hi>acceptable</hi> to you and your <hi>Church,</hi> but even acceptable to <hi>God</hi> himſelf, as being <hi>according to Scripture?</hi> If it is the mind of God, what's the reaſon that you tattle of a <hi>diſpenſing Power</hi> in your <hi>Church</hi> with reſpect to this matter? As if the Mind of God, were altogether inſignificant with you; that let God command what he pleaſe, you will be ſo ſtately as to conceit, that you may by virtue of your <hi>diſpenſing Power,</hi> do juſt what you liſt. And if he don't think good to accept of what you pleaſe to give him, as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of your <hi>Power,</hi> tho 'tis but <hi>Sprinkling,</hi> for <hi>Baptizing</hi> or <hi>Dipping,</hi> he's like to get nothing elſe from you. Yet in your Plea for this <hi>Power,</hi> you do as good as dwindle it into nothing too: for you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:172831:21"/>to make us believe that it only relates to <hi>Circumſtantials,</hi> and the <hi>manner</hi> of Acting, but not to the <hi>Act it ſelf.</hi> Really, Sirs, if this be true, you had better have kept where you were, without the leaſt pretence to this <hi>diſpenſing Power,</hi> for it can do you no Kindneſs at all: For if <hi>Dipping</hi> or <hi>Burying</hi> in Water, be the thing that God requires, then according to your own grant, your <hi>Church</hi> has not <hi>Power</hi> to diſpenſe with this <hi>Act,</hi> and turn it into <hi>another,</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not by any means be the <hi>ſame Act;</hi> which is certainly the Caſe of <hi>Dipping</hi> and <hi>Sprinkling:</hi> For <hi>Sprinkling</hi> and <hi>Baptizing</hi> are certainly two different Things, two different Actions, having two different Forms, and cannot by any means properly be called the ſame. All that you can fairly pretend to, if you be true to your Plea, is, That the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrator is at liberty to <hi>dip,</hi> or put the Perſon <hi>under Water,</hi> divers manner of Ways, as forward, backward, ſideway, toward the Right-Hand, or toward the Left, quickly, or ſlowly; all theſe Things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meerly Circumſtantial; yet all this while <hi>Dipping,</hi> or putting <hi>under Water,</hi> is the <hi>Act</hi> or <hi>Thing</hi> to be done: Which if it be done, the Perſon may truly be ſaid to be <hi>baptized,</hi> notwithſtanding theſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent <hi>Circumſtances;</hi> becauſe the Eſſential Form of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> viz. <hi>Dipping in Water,</hi> is to be found in all theſe ways. But if you only <hi>ſprinkle</hi> a little Water on his Face, that is quite <hi>another Thing;</hi> not <hi>another Circumſtance</hi> in which the ſame Thing is yet done, but clearly <hi>another Act,</hi> in which not the <hi>ſame</hi> but another <hi>Thing</hi> is done; and the Perſon thereby is no more truly baptized, than as if you had given him a Flip or two with a wet Finger: For here is <hi>differentia eſſentialis,</hi> the very Formality of Baptiſm is abſent. So that you had better continue your firſt Compliance with us, than ſtrive as you do in your Second, to run away from us; for 'tis certainly true, that if our Practice be <hi>Right,</hi> (as you know it is) yours muſt of neceſſity be <hi>Wrong:</hi> And all your idle <hi>Greek</hi> Struggles will never be able to make it otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>I muſt, before I conclude, take a little notice of your great Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo formally laid down in your Second Paper; which I had like to have over-look'd and forgot: I confeſs it is here a little out of due place, but it's no great matter, better here than no where, leſt you ſhould think a meer <hi>Senſe</hi> of its <hi>Strength</hi> frighted me from it. The Argument in form appears thus, <hi>An Ordinance once enjoyn'd, and never repeal'd, is always in force: But the Ordinance of Childrens incovenanting was once in the Old Teſtament enjoyn'd, and was never repeal'd.</hi> Ergo, <hi>'Tis yet in Force.</hi> Good now, Sirs, do ſo much as tell us, what is the <hi>Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:172831:22"/>this Argument relates to? or what is it brought to prove? Sirs, Do you urge this <hi>Argument</hi> to prove <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> or do you not? If not, what Buſineſs has it here? If you do, certainly ſuch an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was hardly ever laid down for ſuch a purpoſe, by any that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the leaſt Skill in Logick: For there is not the leaſt mention of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> in any part of the Argument. If you had intended the Proof of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> by it, it ought to have run thus, <hi>An Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance once enjoyn'd, and never repeal'd, is ſtill in force: But the Ordinance of Infant-Baptiſm was once enjoyn'd, and was never repeal'd:</hi> Ergo, <hi>Infant-Baptiſm is ſtill in force.</hi> Now if you had argued thus, and prov'd your <hi>Minor,</hi> you had then done your Buſineſs. But now, Sirs, what is it you have done by this Argument? What <hi>Ordinance</hi> is this that was once enjoyn'd and never repeal'd? One would think you muſt of neceſſity mean either <hi>Circumciſion</hi> or <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> If <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> then that's in force ſtill, and 'tis <hi>Circumciſion</hi> you plead for: If you mean <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> then I deny your <hi>Minor,</hi> and put you to prove that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> was ever enjoyn'd as an <hi>Ordinance</hi> upon <hi>Infants.</hi> But if you mean neither, but only a meer <hi>Incovenanting,</hi> as you call it, altho I do not well know what you mean by it, neither do I underſtand any thing of ſuch an Injunction ſeparate from <hi>Circumciſion;</hi> yet, for Diſcourſe-ſake, I give it you, pray take it and make your beſt of it: <hi>Incovenant</hi> your Children as much as you will, or can, who ſhall hinder you? But then you muſt not ſpeak a Word of their <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> by virtue of this Argument, for it's now ſuppos'd that this Argument neither <hi>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> or <hi>means</hi> Baptiſm, much leſs does it prove their Baptiſm: So that you are as far to ſeek for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> as ever you were, unleſs you had produc'd a <hi>Precept,</hi> or an <hi>Appointment</hi> of God for that purpoſe; otherwiſe all the <hi>Inconvenanting</hi> you talk of will do you no good: For if God had never commanded <hi>Infants</hi> to have been <hi>Circumciſed,</hi> who durſt have done it, notwithſtanding this Plea? So if he had no where commanded <hi>Infants</hi> to be <hi>baptized,</hi> who ſhall dare to do it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſame Plea? Altho you were ſure you had it, which I do not in the leaſt believe, tho I will not at this time diſpute it: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, what need you care whether you have it or no? for you that dare <hi>baptize</hi> your <hi>Infants</hi> without being enjoyn'd, what need you care whether the other be enjoyn'd or no? what need you trouble your ſelves, whether Childrens <hi>incovenanting</hi> were once enjoyn'd or no? or if it was, what matter is it if it ſhould be <hi>repeal'd?</hi> You may as well <hi>baptize</hi> them of your <hi>own pleaſure,</hi> without this Plea, as with it. For if God never appointed it, there's no Plea for it; but if he has
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:172831:22"/>appointed it, there's none againſt it: So that if it be your pleaſure, that <hi>Infants</hi> ſhall be <hi>baptized,</hi> you had as good inſiſt upon your <hi>Churches Power,</hi> and never trouble the World with an Argument about it. And that will be the eaſieſt way for you to anſwer <hi>the three Sheets and a half</hi> already publiſh'd (as you it ſeems are inform'd) by the joint Conſent of the <hi>principal Anabaptiſt Preachers</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> or any other of their Papers: Becauſe you know you have publickly oblig'd your ſelves to give a full anſwer to all the Queſtions in them, or to any other Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions or Objections that can be ſent to you in the mean time. And the <hi>Remark</hi> that you make at the ſame time, is ſo <hi>Remarkable,</hi> that I ſhall make a <hi>Remark</hi> upon it. Your <hi>Remark</hi> is this, <hi>That ſurely had not the Anabaptiſts thought you had advanc'd ſomething of moment, in your two Mercuries about Infant-Baptiſm, they would never have call'd in ſuch aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for the anſwering of them, or made ſuch a ſtir about them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Really, Sirs, I plainly perceive, that you are fully reſolv'd, that every thing ſhall make for your Credit, let it be what it will: For here, becauſe ſome few of them conſented and thought good, your two <hi>Mercuries</hi> ſhould be <hi>anſwer'd,</hi> and accordingly were ſo; you meerly make that an Argument of the <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Moment</hi> of your Matter contain'd therein: And yet, becauſe the <hi>Gentleman</hi> in his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimadverſions,</hi> did but omit that impertinent Paſſage of the <hi>Ruler's Daughter,</hi> tho we may reaſonably ſuppoſe it was, becauſe he almoſt thought it below a Man to take notice of it; how bravely could you improve that poor Omiſſion againſt him, and make that too an Argument of the great Strength and Moment of that Paſſage? So that you are the moſt fortunate Men alive. Your being <hi>anſwer'd</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>Greatneſs</hi> in you; not <hi>anſwering</hi> you, ſignifies the ſame? Every thing, it ſeems, works for the Reputation of the <hi>Athenian Society:</hi> What is it that Men ſo priviledg'd may not venture upon? You ſay likewiſe, <hi>If any Anabaptiſts are diſoblig'd by your Reflections upon thoſe call'd Anabaptiſts in</hi> Germany; you promiſe, or threaten, (for my part I know not which) <hi>to put the Matter in its true Light, which has never been done yet.</hi> Sirs, the main thing, I think, that they commonly mind in that caſe, is to obſerve the very great Folly and Weakneſs of you <hi>Pedo-baptiſts,</hi> who generally are mighty apt and forward to make a clutter about the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> when you ought, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof, to give us a good ſound Argument for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm.</hi> We cannot imagine what you mean in ſo doing, or what ſhould make you ſo <hi>ſilly,</hi> from time to time, without the leaſt Occaſion, Provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Reaſon, to be ſo <hi>miſerably impertinent.</hi> Good now, Sirs, do
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:172831:23"/>ſo much as tell us ſeriouſly, what it is you propound to your ſelves in your ſo doing: Do you give it us as an Argument for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> or do you not; if not, then you your ſelves don't look upon it as any thing to your purpoſe, with reſpect to that Controverſy; if you do, you are as much out in your <hi>Methods,</hi> as the Man was in his <hi>Tools,</hi> that bought a <hi>Hammer</hi> and a <hi>Chizzel</hi> to make his Neighbour a <hi>Dubblet.</hi> But I'm afraid there is ſomething worſe in it yet than all this; and that is, you urge theſe things commonly, for no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, than thereby to expoſe the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> to the <hi>Contempt</hi> and <hi>Hatred</hi> of <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>undiſcerning</hi> People; whom you are willing to hope, will believe you in all you ſay, without examining any thing: And from their great skill in Logick, will conclude, that all <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> muſt be ſuch, or one way or another as bad. If this be your deſign, Sirs, 'tis very bad; and 'tis no marvel, if thoſe you call <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſhould be <hi>diſoblig'd</hi> at it: but if you can clear your ſelves, pray do; for my part, I ſhould be very glad herein to be miſtaken. And that which aggravates your Folly herein, (to ſay no worſe) is, that you cannot but know, that if your <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> were in the humour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminate, what an <hi>Augean Stable</hi> might ſoon be made of your <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Oxen:</hi> ſuch a one as all the River <hi>Alphaeus</hi> would never be able to <hi>cleanſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, if this <hi>true Light</hi> you talk of, be a <hi>new Light,</hi> as your words ſeem to imply, it may then juſtly be ſuſpected to be your <hi>own Invention,</hi> and ſo nothing but <hi>meer Darkneſs;</hi> but if it be an <hi>old Light,</hi> then it will be the <hi>ſame</hi> as it was before, and I'm afraid too near a kin to <hi>Guy Faux</hi>'s Dark-Lanthorn, to be good for any thing. However, Gentlemen, uſe your Pleaſure, do what ſeemeth good in your own Eyes; only remember, <hi>that for all theſe things God will bring you to Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:172831:23"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>HAving a little Paper-room left, which I was not aware of till the <hi>Preſs</hi> convinc'd me of it, I ſhall a little reflect upon two or three things, which hitherto I have wholly omitted.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is, that <hi>ſtrange</hi> and <hi>prodigious</hi> Ignorance, you ſeem to be guilty of, when you inſinuate to the World, that there is not one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Female-Baptiſm</hi> in all the Scripture. Sirs, Is it likely that you ſhould be fit Perſons to manage ſuch a Controverſy, <hi>ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily</hi> and <hi>convincingly,</hi> wherein, and concerning which, you appear to be ſo <hi>aſtoniſhingly</hi> ignorant? yet this ſtrange <hi>Ignorance</hi> of yours, is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with as ſtrange a <hi>Confidence,</hi> with which you boldly, and in the face of the Sun, challenge your <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> to ſhew where they have one Inſtance of <hi>Female-Baptiſm.</hi> Really, Sirs, in my opinion, it is (at leaſt) a very great ſhame for any Man, or <hi>Woman</hi> either, (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to Chriſtianity) of the meaneſt parts imaginable, to be ſo <hi>horridly ignorant,</hi> as here you appear to be: How much more then is your <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Blame</hi> increas'd and aggravated, when we conſider with what <hi>Magnifying Glaſſes</hi> you look upon your ſelves, and what <hi>publick</hi> Pretences you make to Parts, Learning, Wit, and almoſt, if not altogether, <hi>univerſal</hi> Underſtanding? You confidently inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, that <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> is as plainly to be found in Scripture as that of <hi>Adult Females.</hi> Now, Sirs, if this did but appear to be <hi>truth,</hi> we ſhould then immediately have done diſputing; but it is ſo far from appearing to be <hi>truth,</hi> that the contrary is not only eaſily demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, but you <hi>your ſelves</hi> ſhall be my <hi>Witneſs,</hi> that it is directly <hi>falſe:</hi> for you plainly confeſs, in words at length, that <hi>Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> is not <hi>expreſly</hi> to be found in Scripture. Now then, if <hi>Womens</hi> being <hi>baptiz'd,</hi> is <hi>expreſly</hi> to be found in Scripture, then you are <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> againſt <hi>your ſelves</hi> of the <hi>Falſeneſs</hi> of that Suggeſtion: But the <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of <hi>Women</hi> is <hi>expreſly</hi> to be found in Scripture; <hi>Ergo.</hi> See <hi>Act.</hi> 8.12. &amp; 16.14, 15. All that I ſhall ſay more to this particular, is only this; that as you have publickly <hi>abus'd,</hi> and endeavour'd to <hi>deceive</hi> the World, by your ignorant, raſh, and falſe Inſinuations, eſpecially in this matter, wherein you are ſo eaſily <hi>detected</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed;</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:172831:24"/>ſo you ought at leaſt to make as <hi>publick</hi> an <hi>Acknowledgment</hi> and <hi>Recantation,</hi> of this <hi>Injury</hi> done to the World by this <hi>blind,</hi> yet <hi>bold</hi> Attempt of yours: for it's no ſmall matter thus to abuſe the World, and make no conſcience of making Compenſation.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing I would a little note, is a piece of <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Logick,</hi> ſomewhat agreeble to the Ignorance juſt now complain'd of. When you tell us, that if Children <hi>do behold the Face of God</hi> in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>as</hi> (ſay you) <hi>our Saviour ſays; then it follows, that they have Faith in Heaven; and</hi> (conſequently) <hi>why not on Earth?</hi> To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That Children do, or may <hi>behold</hi> the Face of God in <hi>Heaven,</hi> I will not deny; yet I profeſs, I do not remember where our Saviour tells us ſo: however, it does not in the leaſt <hi>follow,</hi> that <hi>therefore</hi> they have <hi>Faith</hi> in Heaven; but it rather ſtrongly implies the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; becauſe <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Sight,</hi> are plainly oppos'd to each other, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. where the Apoſtle plainly tells us, that <hi>here,</hi> while we walk by <hi>Faith,</hi> we walk not by <hi>Sight:</hi> Implying, that while <hi>Faith</hi> continues, <hi>Sight</hi> is abſent; conſequently, when <hi>Sight</hi> comes, <hi>Faith</hi> diſappears. Tho 'tis true, <hi>here,</hi> whilſt we are <hi>in the Body,</hi> we are abſent from the Lord; and to ſee him that is <hi>inviſible,</hi> muſt needs <hi>now</hi> be an Act of <hi>Faith,</hi> according to the Text you quote, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.27. But the time will come, when <hi>Faith</hi> will be turn'd into <hi>Viſion,</hi> and <hi>Promiſe,</hi> which is the <hi>ground</hi> of Faith, into <hi>Fruition,</hi> which is the <hi>end</hi> of Faith. When we ſhall <hi>ſee Face to Face, ſee him as he is, and know as we are known,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.12. 1 Joh. 3.2. So that it's ſo far from being evident, that <hi>Infants</hi> have, or ſhall have <hi>Faith</hi> in Heaven, that it is, at leaſt, a very great Queſtion, whether ſuch a thing can fairly be ſaid of the greateſt <hi>actual Believer</hi> in the World. But further, ſuppoſe we ſhould give you the <hi>Premiſes,</hi> and grant you that <hi>Infants</hi> may have <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>Heaven;</hi> your Concluſion is not a little to be <hi>admir'd,</hi> or rather your ſelves, for your ſtrange skill in <hi>Theological</hi> Logick. Sirs, do you indeed look upon this to be good Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that becauſe a thing is, or may be, thus or ſo, in <hi>Heaven,</hi> therefore it is, and muſt be ſo here on <hi>Earth?</hi> If you do not, why do you talk at this <hi>extravagant</hi> rate; and endeavour to impoſe that upon others, which you do not <hi>believe</hi> your ſelves? If you do, I muſt acknowledg, that all the <hi>Wit</hi> I have is not ſufficient to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Greatneſs of your <hi>Folly;</hi> yet take a taſte however: In <hi>Heaven,</hi> the Saints ſhall be <hi>wholly</hi> freed from all <hi>Sin, Sorrow</hi> and <hi>Trouble,</hi> of what nature ſoever: <hi>Ergo, Why not ſo here on Earth?</hi> In <hi>Heaven</hi> Saints ſhall be <hi>immortal:</hi> Ergo, <hi>Why not ſo here on Earth?</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:172831:24"/>In <hi>Heaven,</hi> the now <hi>vile Bodies</hi> of Saints ſhall be <hi>changed,</hi> and be made like unto the <hi>glorious Body</hi> of Chriſt: Ergo, <hi>Why not ſo here on Earth?</hi> with much more of this nature. Certainly, Sirs, there's none could ever have thought you ſo prepoſterouſly ridiculous, if you had not your ſelves <hi>proclaim'd</hi> it upon the <hi>Houſe-top.</hi> What a ſtrange thing it is, that Men ſo <hi>manifeſtly weak,</hi> ſhould yet be ſo <hi>conceitedly ſtrong,</hi> as to ſuppoſe themſelves able to anſwer all the <hi>Queſtions, Arguments</hi> and <hi>Objections,</hi> that can be ſent them from the People call'd <hi>Anabaptiſts?</hi> But I hope you may yet live to ſee your <hi>Vanity,</hi> and ſo get into the Road of learning more <hi>Wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly; I cannot but note, how ſtrangely ſometimes you abuſe your Antagoniſts, in asking them ſuch kind of <hi>Queſtions,</hi> as imply an <hi>Abſurdity</hi> in them, when they are no more <hi>concern'd</hi> in the <hi>Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> than <hi>your ſelves.</hi> As for inſtance, you very reprehenſively ask them, <hi>How the Faith of the Parent can put the Child further off from God:</hi> and <hi>how Children can loſe by Chriſt's Coming, who came to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Sin of the World,</hi> &amp;c. Now, would not any Body be apt to think, that the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> muſt needs hold the <hi>Affirmative</hi> here, in both theſe <hi>Queſtions;</hi> or elſe you muſt needs be very <hi>impertinent</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious</hi> to them, thus <hi>unworthily</hi> to <hi>inſinuate?</hi> Now, Sirs, I challenge you, to give an Inſtance if you can, of any amongſt the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> that ever told you, either in <hi>Word</hi> or <hi>Writing,</hi> that the <hi>Faith</hi> of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> put the <hi>Child</hi> further off from God; or that Children <hi>loſt</hi> any thing by the <hi>Coming of Chriſt:</hi> for certainly, either you do know of ſome ſuch, or you do not: if you do, you ought to put it out of <hi>queſtion,</hi> for your own <hi>Vindication;</hi> and then I ſhall reckon them as <hi>weak</hi> in that, as <hi>you</hi> are in ſome other things: But if you know of none ſuch, what <hi>Shame</hi> ought you to take to your ſelves, for thus diſingenuouſly <hi>miſrepreſenting</hi> your <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> to the World, as if <hi>thoſe</hi> very things were the <hi>Queſtions</hi> in <hi>debate</hi> betwixt you?</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, I ſhall take a little notice what a ſtrange Faculty there is generally in you <hi>Pedo-baptiſts,</hi> of <hi>fawning</hi> one upon another; how apt you are to <hi>magnify</hi> and <hi>extol</hi> one another, for every <hi>little no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> you do upon a Publick-Stage. This has been a <hi>Faſhion</hi> of a long ſtanding amongſt you; that whoever carries the <hi>Thing,</hi> you ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to carry the <hi>Thank:</hi> and whoever <hi>loſes,</hi> you muſt ſtill ride <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant.</hi> And this is the Caſe of your <hi>Poſtſcript-Gentleman,</hi> towards Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi> of <hi>New-England:</hi> Not that he ſo much as attempts to prove, that Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi> did <hi>merit</hi> or <hi>deſerve</hi> any <hi>Honour</hi> for what (he there ſays) he did; but meerly, becauſe Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi> did <hi>ſomething,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:172831:25"/>with which that <hi>Gentleman</hi> was pleas'd, therefore <hi>Honour</hi> will for <hi>ever redound</hi> to Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi> of <hi>New-England:</hi> Whereas, 'tis ten to one if the merit of the Cauſe were but throughly <hi>examin'd,</hi> and <hi>impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially</hi> conſider'd, the <hi>Honour</hi> might <hi>rebound</hi> from Mr. <hi>Elliot,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound</hi> to them which oppos'd him: and why not? for he only tells us, that he openly and <hi>earneſtly</hi> maintain'd the Cauſe of <hi>Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> againſt a ſort of Perſons, who forget that in the Goſpel-Church, the <hi>Promiſe</hi> is to <hi>Believers</hi> and their <hi>Children;</hi> and are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to reckon <hi>Children</hi> among the <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. He ſcarcely ſo much as tells us, much leſs does he <hi>prove,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi> was in the <hi>Truth,</hi> and his <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> in an <hi>Error:</hi> ſo that ſtill for ought we know, the <hi>Honour</hi> might belong to the <hi>other ſide,</hi> to <hi>them</hi> who openly and <hi>earneſtly oppoſed</hi> the Cauſe of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> againſt a ſort of Perſons, who forget that in the Goſpel-Church, the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> he <hi>alludes</hi> to, is any <hi>otherwiſe,</hi> to <hi>any Body,</hi> than it is to <hi>every Body;</hi> or to Believers <hi>Children,</hi> any otherwiſe than it was to <hi>Believers themſelves:</hi> namely, upon <hi>Condition</hi> of their <hi>believing,</hi> and performing the Conditions required in order thereunto; as their <hi>Parents</hi> before them were <hi>fain</hi> to do, before they had any <hi>Intereſt</hi> therein; for the <hi>Promiſe</hi> belongs to <hi>all the World,</hi> upon thoſe <hi>Conditions,</hi> and to <hi>none in the World</hi> without them. For if it belong to any without <hi>Condition,</hi> then the Promiſe is abſolute, and belongs as much to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers</hi> and <hi>their Children,</hi> as it can do to any Body elſe. And it's worth obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that theſe very Perſons, unto whom <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks theſe Words, were not themſelves <hi>Believers</hi> as <hi>yet,</hi> but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers,</hi> when <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake theſe Words unto them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Neither has this <hi>Gentleman</hi> told us at all, what Infants are the <hi>better</hi> for Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi>'s reckoning them <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> he has not ſo much as told us, that Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi> proved them ſo to be: And pray what <hi>Advantage</hi> can it be to poor <hi>Infants</hi> to be <hi>miſcalled,</hi> and reckoned what they are not? What if Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi> of <hi>New-England</hi> had reckoned <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Believers</hi> to be <hi>Lawyers, Counſellors,</hi> and <hi>Judges,</hi> would this have done the <hi>poor Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> any Good, or have provoked any <hi>wiſe Man</hi> to have carried any of them a <hi>Fee</hi> to plead his Cauſe? Or, what <hi>Honour</hi> would have been due to Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi> for ſuch an <hi>idle Encomium,</hi> any more than to thoſe that ſhould oppoſe him therein? But what kind of Folks thoſe are that are unwilling to grant that <hi>of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> for my part I know not: Certainly there's no People in the World more guilty of ſuch a thing than <hi>Pedo-Baptiſts.</hi> I am very much of the Mind that the <hi>Gentleman</hi> that talks of it, never met with a <hi>Baptiſt</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:172831:25"/>in his Life, that could juſtly be charg'd with ſuch a thing: But you <hi>Pedo-baptiſts</hi> generally ſay what you liſt, (eſpecially in this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy) and matter not what you charge your <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> with; for if you did, you would either not do as you do, or elſe often be <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd</hi> where you are not: For it's well known, that there are a great many of the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> ſo far from what's here <hi>inſinuated,</hi> that they do ſtedfaſtly believe that <hi>all Infants in the World,</hi> dying in Infancy, ſhall certainly be ſaved; and ſome of them have writ Books to the ſame purpoſe, againſt the <hi>Cruelty</hi> of ſome <hi>Pedo-baptiſts</hi> that damn them by <hi>Millions:</hi> And tho there may poſſibly be ſome of the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> that may not be of that Perſwaſion, yet the <hi>worſt</hi> of them believe as well as the <hi>moſt</hi> of you, concerning them.</p>
            <p>It may alſo be worth while to enquire wherein lay the <hi>Greatneſs</hi> and <hi>Worth</hi> of that thing in Mr. <hi>Elliot,</hi> to be ſo <hi>earneſt</hi> to bring <hi>Infants</hi> under the <hi>Bond</hi> of the <hi>Covenant?</hi> May we ſuppoſe, that <hi>Infants</hi> being brought under this <hi>Bond,</hi> was really the <hi>Act</hi> and <hi>Deed</hi> of Mr. <hi>Elliot?</hi> for ſo indeed the Words plainly ſeem to imply; and if ſo, then it ſeems they never were under this <hi>Bond</hi> before, neither would it have been ſo <hi>now,</hi> if it had not been for <hi>earneſt</hi> Mr. <hi>Elliot:</hi> Let any one judg then of the <hi>Excellency</hi> of this <hi>Act.</hi> Beſides, what the <hi>Gentleman</hi> means by the <hi>Bond</hi> of the Covenant, who can imagin? unleſs by <hi>Bond</hi> of the Covenant, he means the <hi>Duties</hi> which the Covenant <hi>binds</hi> and <hi>obliges</hi> People to perform towards God, I cannot gueſs at his Meaning: and if ſo, then what <hi>Honour</hi> is due to Mr. <hi>Elliot,</hi> may ſoon be diſcern'd, for bringing poor <hi>uncapable Infants</hi> under an <hi>Obligation</hi> to perform the <hi>Duties</hi> of the Covenant, and affording them no more <hi>Strength</hi> to perform them, than they had before they were brought under this <hi>Obligation;</hi> and ſo through Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi>'s <hi>Earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> poor <hi>Infants</hi> are undone for ever. But the beſt of it is, this is all <hi>falſe,</hi> a meer <hi>idle Conceit</hi> that has nothing in it; or elſe Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi>'s Honour had been rais'd upon the <hi>Ruin</hi> of <hi>Infants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have now done, when I have only told you, that <hi>the principal Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt Preachers in</hi> London, (as you call them) were not at all concern'd in the <hi>drawing up</hi> of theſe few Sheets: for I can aſſure you it was done by a very <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>private</hi> Hand, by one, and one only, that is ſo <hi>far too</hi> from being a <hi>principal Preacher,</hi> or any Preacher at all, as that he is not accounted worthy to be a Member amongſt them: neither had they, whom you call <hi>principal Preachers,</hi> nor any in a <hi>publick Capacity,</hi> any hand either in the <hi>Compoſing</hi> or <hi>Publiſhing</hi> of theſe Lines: But the <hi>Author</hi> was ſo <hi>hardy,</hi> as to get it printed of his <hi>own accord,</hi> and upon
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:172831:26"/>his <hi>own account,</hi> without being concern'd who were <hi>pleas'd</hi> or <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd</hi> at his ſo doing. Wherefore, whatſoever <hi>Defects</hi> appear to be in them, they are all <hi>his own;</hi> it is not fit, that <hi>any Body</hi> ſhould ſo much as <hi>ſhare</hi> with him in any thing that may be <hi>juſtly due</hi> upon that account; and whatſoever <hi>mean</hi> or <hi>unworthy</hi> Apprehenſions you may have either of the <hi>Author</hi> or his <hi>Work,</hi> if you think it worth your while to take any publick Notice of it, pray ſpeak <hi>directly</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> and to the <hi>Matter in hand,</hi> without <hi>diſingenuous</hi> and <hi>impertinent</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections: for I muſt ſignify to you, that as <hi>mean</hi> as the <hi>Author</hi> is, he is not altogether ſo <hi>ſilly,</hi> as to take <hi>idle</hi> and <hi>impertinent</hi> Reflections for <hi>ſolid</hi> and <hi>ſatisfactory</hi> Anſwers; but looks upon all <hi>ſuch Perſons,</hi> as the <hi>greateſt</hi> and <hi>worſt</hi> Sort of <hi>Fools</hi> in the World, that take <hi>Sanctuary</hi> in ſuch <hi>rotten</hi> and <hi>deſolate</hi> Buildings. Gentlemen, I do not <hi>charge</hi> you with any ſuch thing aforehand, but only give you this timely <hi>Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that if you ſhould happen to <hi>act</hi> at that <hi>rate</hi> in your <hi>Anſwers</hi> to <hi>me,</hi> or <hi>any Body elſe,</hi> you might appear to be the more <hi>inexcuſable:</hi> But if there ſhould appear to be any <hi>little Strength</hi> in theſe <hi>Lines,</hi> pray do not think that you have yet got, either <hi>all,</hi> or the <hi>principal Strength</hi> that you may expect from the People you call <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> if further occaſion require: For ſo long as <hi>the Way of the Lord</hi> continues <hi>Strength to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright,</hi> you may not expect to <hi>ſee</hi> an <hi>end</hi> of their <hi>Strength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I fully deſign'd to have <hi>ended,</hi> but unleſs I had written ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what <hi>leſs</hi> in my <hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> I plainly perceive I muſt be <hi>oblig'd</hi> to write a <hi>little more,</hi> becauſe my <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> has <hi>beſpoke</hi> a little more <hi>Paper</hi> than I firſt intended. I ſhall therefore <hi>briefly</hi> offer two or three <hi>Arguments</hi> to Conſideration, againſt <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> without any <hi>enlargement</hi> at all, to <hi>defend</hi> or <hi>ſecure</hi> any part thereof, till I plainly <hi>ſee</hi> or <hi>know</hi> what <hi>Objections</hi> or <hi>Exceptions</hi> our <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> ſhall pleaſe to make againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. The <hi>New Teſtament</hi> doth <hi>plainly, fully</hi> and <hi>ſufficiently</hi> declare to us who are the <hi>true Subjects</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> But the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> doth neither <hi>plainly, fully</hi> nor <hi>ſufficiently</hi> declare to us that <hi>Infants</hi> are the <hi>true Subjects</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> Ergo, <hi>Infants</hi> are not the <hi>true Subjects</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. None ought to be <hi>Baptized</hi> without <hi>knowing</hi> what they do, and <hi>conſenting</hi> thereunto: But <hi>Little Infants</hi> are not capable either of <hi>Knowledg</hi> or <hi>Conſent</hi> in that matter. Ergo, <hi>Little Infants</hi> ought not to be <hi>Baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. That which there is no <hi>Precept for,</hi> nor <hi>Precedent</hi> of, nor <hi>Promiſe unto</hi> in all the <hi>Word of God,</hi> is not of <hi>Divine Authority:</hi> But
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:172831:26"/>there is no <hi>Precept for, Precedent of,</hi> nor <hi>Promiſe unto</hi> the <hi>Baptizing</hi> of <hi>Infants</hi> in all the <hi>Word of God.</hi> Ergo, <hi>Baptizing</hi> of <hi>Infants</hi> is not of <hi>Divine Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. If <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> be of <hi>Divine Authority,</hi> then it is (by the appointment of God) for ſome <hi>good Ends</hi> and <hi>Purpoſes:</hi> But <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> is not (by the appointment of God) for any good <hi>Ends</hi> and <hi>Purpoſes. Ergo,</hi> It is not of <hi>Divine Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. That <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> that is not <hi>agreeable</hi> to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>John the Baptiſt, Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> is not of <hi>Divine Authority:</hi> But the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> is not <hi>agreeable</hi> to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>John the Baptiſt, Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles. Ergo,</hi> The <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> is not of <hi>Divine Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. If <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> be of <hi>Divine Authority,</hi> then it is a <hi>Sin</hi> in <hi>Parents</hi> to omit <hi>baptizing</hi> their <hi>Infants:</hi> But it is not a <hi>Sin</hi> in <hi>Parents,</hi> to omit <hi>baptizing</hi> their <hi>Infants.</hi> Ergo, <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> is not of <hi>Divine Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 7. That which is <hi>ſubſtantially</hi> and <hi>ſeverely</hi> forbidden by the <hi>Word of God,</hi> is not of <hi>Divine Authority:</hi> But <hi>baptizing Infants</hi> in the <hi>Name of the Lord,</hi> is <hi>ſubſtantially</hi> and <hi>ſeverely</hi> forbidden by the <hi>Word of God.</hi> Ergo, <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> is not of <hi>Divine Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay nothing at preſent in the <hi>Defence</hi> of theſe <hi>Arguments,</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leave them (thus <hi>briefly</hi> and <hi>nakedly</hi> laid down) to the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of any that ſhall pleaſe to <hi>peruſe</hi> them: But when I <hi>perceive</hi> what it is that my <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> have to ſay againſt them, or where their <hi>Anſwers</hi> or <hi>Exceptions</hi> will be chiefly <hi>concern'd,</hi> I ſhall then reckon my ſelf <hi>oblig'd</hi> to <hi>prove</hi> whatſoever is <hi>deny'd,</hi> or elſe <hi>ſubmit</hi> to the <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Anſwers</hi> given.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 23. l. 6. r. <hi>came.</hi> P. 24. l. 5. r. <hi>will do you no ſervice.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
